Fifth and last but by no means least, as far as he's concerned anyway, Michele Mendetti of Italy.
So before we get underway, we've had a question from one of our punters via Twitter and thank you to all the people who have contacted both Leon and myself on Twitter about the spray onto the surface of the diving pit.
Could you explain please, sir?
Yes, I could.
So just on the other side of the flowers there, what you're seeing is ripples on the surface of the water.
Now they're caused by, well, what can best be described as hose pipes pointing in from the side of the diving pool.
Now the intention behind this is just to disturb.
There we are, the spray's well done.
Thanks very much, director.
Look at that.
The spray coming there just to the right of screen is actually disturbing the water.
The reason for this is the divers need to know exactly where the surface of the water is.
If there are no sprays the water becomes very very still and you focus on the bottom of the diving pool which is of course another 5.8 metres away from the surface.
So the divers need to be very precise when they're going to grab their hands and punch that hole in the water and the ripples there ensure the divers can make that judgement correctly most of the time.
Well that's the problem anyway.
hopefully resolved for them today with that spray onto the surface.
Hope that has answered the question which a few people have posed to us.
Time to get underway with the first of the twenty-nine divers.
Six rounds.
Remember, five rounds with the women, six round with the men and the opening diver will be Ethan Warren from Australia and a three point zero degree of difficulty in the pike position to start off with is his back.
Two and a half somersaults.
Little bit of splash being thrown up there.
You can just see the Australian fans in there, you know, agreeing with me.
Beautiful takeoff.
Always tricky opening up the contest.
3.0 only, just over a little bit of vertical.
See the splash being thrown up.
It's only going to get sevens.
Ethan needs to be diving a little bit better than that to put some pressure on these guys.
He's an exceptional performer.
Let's wait and see.
My favorite number.
Number sixty-three.
It's back again.
Three sevens times three.
We've had that a lot in the women's.
I presume we'll get it quite a few times in the men's as well.
Sixty-three for Warren.
Now, Damien Seeley of France.
It's a bit like a bodybuilder, isn't it?
Muscles there.
Straight over from the excel center.
Absolutely.
Inward two and a half somersaults.
Might be a bit of splash here.
Well, just a little bit, but you'd be surprised how exceptional this guy is.
Yes, he is super bulky.
I think he just needs to look at weights in order to gain muscle size.
Incredible, but look at the power he generates.
Inward two and a half, way above the diving board.
Effortless dive, just making a little bit of a mistake on the entry into the water there.
It'll get mid-60s, but in the men's competition, you want to be sailing over 70 and even into the 80s to ensure qualification.
So Damien Seeley's opening dive produces 67.50.
Remember, three marks that you'll see without a line through them are the ones that count and you'll multiply that by the degree of difficulty.
3.0 on that occasion.
On to the first of the Chinese.
Here comes He Chong.
Back two and a half somersaults with Pike, 3.0 and unusually.
The Chinese are separated by quite some way, so you have to wait until way into the contest before you see the second, but here comes the first of Chinese, the world champion.
Yeah, he's a defending Olympic champion also and looking in fine form here.
Only 25 years old, already Olympic champion four years ago and he'll be looking to retain his title tomorrow night but he still has to get, look how easy does that dive.
Feet pointing down, this will get eight and a halfs.
It's not as good as I've seen him do it but just showing his pure class.
Well, that's the marker for everybody else to follow in round one.
Eight and an eight point five times three.
Just having a quick scowl at his coach.
Give him what for.
Tell him how he can improve and I'm sure he knows exactly what he has to do.
In with three and a half somersaults with Tuck who will go in for a big starter here because that's a three point four degree of difficulty for his opener.
Oh, and it's a beauty as well.
Wow.
So Giveny is not going to give anything away today.
He is DD'd up to the max.
Look at that table down his back.
We'll talk more about that later.
I'm not quite sure how much of a benefit it is.
Obviously, it's not affecting his dive because that's 3.4 degree of difficulty.
Inward, standing backwards, spinning forward.
That's a monster start.
Look at that, 81.
that's why I call brave we see all in the women some people go over 2.7 2.8 he's gone in there straight away so I'm gonna make a statement here and he comes a big dive straight on would you believe that's one of his easier dives 3.4 exciting down a notch but not by much to Daniel Arroyo of Mexico 3.3 on this reverse two and a half one and a half twists
Oh my goodness, he's a little bit close to the diving board there.
You'll see on the replay, his tutsis come a little bit too close for comfort for me.
Look at this, leaning over the diving board, squeezing into the pike shape there.
Oh, he doesn't really want to be any closer than that.
Losing the control of the dive as he goes into the water.
Oh, this is the aerial shot.
Oh, he's all right.
Calm down.
The judges should penalize.
I wouldn't give him more than a five or a five point five for that.
And we've got some cold water, please.
Yeah, well done.
Daniel Arroyo, 61.05 and nearly a pedicure for free.
Stefan Feck of Germany.
I'm sure our Irish viewers are enjoying that pronunciation.
That's correct.
F-E-C-K is his surname.
Back two and a half somersaults with pike, 3.0 degree of difficulty.
So we've come from 3.4 to 3.3 and back to normality if you like for this pike dive for Stefan Feck.
needed to be good and I think that is a little bit off the mark for Stefan normally a very very solid diver two Germans in this Stefan the first one here we are backward two and a half in the pike position just bending at the hips good pike shape looks good till they're just short of vertical landing short as he goes in it's only going to get seven and a half and won't score over 70 points in a lower degree of difficulty needs to be nailed work to do for Stefan
feeling their way into the competition and Stefan Fek 7.5 across the board, multiplied by three, 67.50.
So we're giving you diving and a maths lesson at the same time.
You get value from us, don't you?
Now to Contreras Bracho of Venezuela.
Pike position for this inward two and a half.
Oh, steady start from the Venezuelan, his first Olympic games.
Only 21 years old.
And if he continues to dive like that, I'm sure he'll be very happy.
Watching him in training, a little bit hit and miss.
This is one of his better dives.
Straight up and down.
Needs to be a safe distance from the diving board, which he is.
Inward spinning forwards.
Yeah, it's technically proficient.
And it's a reasonable dive.
It's seven and a half, probably.
Eight, maybe.
Let's see.
Well, interesting enough, we've gone from the 63s to the 67.5, being the current currency for a lot of the diamonds.
That's the fourth mark of 67.5 we've seen today.
Cesar Castro, our Brazil, forwards two and a half with one twist.
No, it's beautifully executed.
It's a very easy dive though.
Lots of the divers choosing to use the more complicated twisting dives.
Cesar here, lots of the girls use this dive.
Not taking anything away from the way Cesar cruises that dive.
I still think he could add another twist.
You'll see a lot of divers doing a double twist here.
says are just going for the single twist maybe later in his program yeah he does use the forward two and a half two twists later in his program so starting easy it's paid off for him though 73.5 decent start for the brazilian puts him in equals second place now this man hasn't been in the olympics for 12 years kenny yo oh well done kenny
29 years old.
Used to dive against him myself.
And he is certainly going to be relying on that wealth of experience of international competition to see him through this preliminary.
He's a very neat and tidy diver.
Should sneak over 70 points for that one.
Little bit of splash as he goes in.
Good board timing.
He's got Chinese coaches to look after him or to put him through his paces at his home in Malaysia.
And here he is in the prelim.
71.30.
Yeah, just mentioning he was involved in the diving competition in 2000 Sydney.
Hasn't competed at the Olympics since his first Olympics in four for the Malaysian.
Now the second of the Germans.
Here's Patrick Housding back two and a half somersaults with Pike for his opening gambit.
Here's one to watch.
Oh, what a dive.
You're looking for the vertical entry into the water with no splash.
That's exactly what the judges are looking for, and that's exactly what Patrick has delivered on his first round dive.
If he gets over 70 points, he keeps himself well within the mix.
This is only 3.0, so it needs to be good, and it is just that.
Yeah, I think you'd be happy with the return on that.
All eights.
Seventy-two for Patrick Housing.
Give me a kiss to the uh friends and family back home.
Plenty of them here I think.
A lot of people in Europe certainly have made the journey over to London to support their divers and uh quite a few from North America as well.
Now, from the Ukraine, here's
Oh, Peguro's not messing around either.
He's coming out all guns blazing.
It's a game of tactics, actually.
If you come out with a big degree of difficulty, which is exactly what Alexi's doing here, an inward three and a half.
We've seen one already, and he's nailed that one.
That's going to get eights, 3.4 degree of difficulty.
It's going to put him high up on the leaderboard.
Speaking of boards, he's not wise a safe distance away from the diving board.
I know lots of you at home like gasp every time a diver comes near.
That's pretty safe.
Just eighty one.
Good.
Good opening dive.
Yeah.
Goes level with the Kuznetov of Russia with that opening dive.
Now, Javier Garcia looking to reach the semifinals for the first time.
Always been knocked out in the prelims with Beijing and in Athens.
Back two and a half for him to start with.
Oh, it's a good start from Javier.
Yeah, third Olympic Games.
He'll be looking to progress further.
He's in good shape.
He's been working hard.
So, what can he do today?
That's his opening dive.
His easiest one.
A little bit of discrepancy as he went in there.
He should sneak seven and a half, maybe even a couple of eights.
Sometimes a bit of a shaky start.
Let's see how he goes on with the rest of his program.
Yeah, judges concur with Leon.
7.5s across the board.
I'll give him a total just outside the top placings in seventh place.
Now on to the American, Chris Colwell.
Eighth at the World Champs in Rome back in 2009.
Ninth here in February at the competition that took place in this very pool.
Back two and a half somersaults with pike opening gambit for Colwell.
Oh, sneaky.
It was nice.
Looked like he was going to over-rotate as he went in, but very cleverly saves the dive by bending, arching through the back, bending the knees, giving the impression that he's completely vertical.
So a superb start there for Colwell.
Obviously, knowing exactly where he is in the air.
When you're spinning backwards, you can only ever see where you've been.
So you have to judge when to let go.
And Chris showing his experience there, 27 years old.
And he got that down all right.
Remember, just the top 18 from 29 starters will go through.
Good opening gambit by Chris Colwell.
72 for him.
Joins Patrick Housding on that score.
Down to Mathieu Rosset of France, seventh in Shanghai for the last World Championships.
Nice oh very nice indeed.
It's a big dive to start with and it's a tough one, too It's only three point three.
I personally think it should be worth more than this.
He's standing backwards He goes swinging the arms one and a half twist two and a half somersaults Wow, and he does a fantastic job on that entry that's gonna put him top of the pile or near his damn What a dive from the young Frenchman
Well, the judges are finding it hard to compute because they're still waiting for that score to come through as you watch another replay.
Look at them spreading the air out there with his hands and causing that suction in the rip entry.
Look at the scores.
That's the biggest so far.
Eighty-four point one five for the Frenchman.
Can be delighted with that.
Had a very, very good string of performances in Shanghai last year.
I think it was a bit of a surprise to everybody.
Now, the young Canadian Francois Imbaudoulac.
Going for a 3.0 to open his campaign.
Inward two and a half semisaults with Pike.
Yeah, it's neat and tidy.
A little bit, maybe lacking a little bit of strength on his takeoff there.
Some of the other divers completing the dive more easily than Francois.
Squeezing into that pike shape.
You can just see there, he didn't really have a lot of drop time, but it's still straight up and down.
He'll get close to 70 points.
Only 21 years old, first Olympic Games.
I've not seen him dive before.
69 for him.
Just a question, there's a bit of facial hair there.
Swimmers tend to take everything off, body hair, leg hair, facial hair.
Is it a precursor for a good dive or not?
Well, as long as you're impressing the judges with your good looks, that's all that matters.
That's probably why you didn't do any better than you did.
Uh Ilya Zakharov now with an inward three and a half somersault with tuck.
3.4 degree of difficulty on this.
Yep.
Zakharov is not messing around either.
We saw Givenny earlier on in the rounds and these boys are doing their beach weights at home and they're flexing their muscles today.
These are big dives.
Nowhere to go.
Wow.
Cruising that already complete uh competed here at these games and he's going to be strong today.
This is going to get well over 80 points.
Superb opening round dive.
Is that the lead?
Oh, he is the lead by some way by five points.
He's just checking on the uh scores.
So, it's just uh by a couple of points but it is the lead for Zach 86.70.
That's an impressive way to start.
Now, here's a man who a few weeks ago didn't
We'll explain why after we've seen the first dive from Alexandre Departee.
It's a back two and a half somersaults with Pike.
Yeah, Gia's tipping over as he goes into the water.
As you can imagine, Alex, with his wealth of experience, two Olympic medals from the previous two games in this event, both of them silver.
Technically, absolutely superb.
Any young divers around the world watching this, you wouldn't go far wrong looking at Alexandre Departee's technique.
But everyone can make those slight errors of judgement and Alex just tipping over a vertical as he punches a hole here.
Look at that super slow-mo showing the air being sucked down with the diver into the water.
Now why was he almost not here?
Because he hit his head on the diving board in spectacular fashion in Rome a few weeks before.
More on that a little later on.
There was a real question mark over as to whether he'd be here or not.
He is here.
He is competing, as is Ilya Kavasha.
Oh, 3.4 from him.
No messing on an in with three and a half somersault.
He's going for the big dive to start with in the tuck position.
Kavashia nails it as well.
Now I'm interested to observe and to watch the game of tactics being played by both Russian divers and both Ukrainian divers.
All of them opting for this opening dive which is tricky, it's complicated, it's 3.4 and if you get it right it puts you straight up in the business end of the field from round one.
Now what does that do to your competitors when they're trying to catch up?
I think it's the game of tactics being well played.
Yeah, though not quite as well executed as some previous ones, but still a decent mark as it would be with the three point four degree of difficulty.
Seventy six point five zero for Kavasha.
Sebastian Castaneda of Columbia in with two and a half.
Oh, it's a nice dive.
Very precise.
You can see the difference between the inward three and a half and the inward two and a half.
Inward three and a half, there's a lot of spins to get in.
The two and a half opting for the pike position.
It's a lot slower rotation.
very well placed but when the guys are slotting in those big big big degrees of difficulty you're going to be very hard to keep up with them with such low degree of difficulty well let's see what he has in the rest of his program to play catch up because that's what i have to do after that 72 for the columbian the big cheer greeting at the arrival of the first of the two british divers today and hopefully like we've seen previous british divers do he'll soak up some of the atmosphere before he gets involved in his opening dive he'll be
Moving away from the end of the diving ball, it's a back two and a half somersaults with Pike.
Chris Mears with Jack Law to come in a couple of divers time, 3.0 degree of difficulty in the Pike position.
Oh, superb start for the first of Team GB.
There's his mum and dad.
I've obviously seen him compete already in the three meter synchronized springboard.
Fantastic job coming fifth in that event.
Beautiful elevation, squeezing into the pike shape.
All-important entry into the water, tipping over a little bit.
Nice steady start from Chris Mears, only 19.
Yeah, could have done a little better on the entry.
Let's see what the a bit harsh from the judges.
Maybe 7.5 67.50 Chris Mears reasonable start though for him puts him in the decent order early on.
Oh, it's steady.
It's on his head.
Little bit short as he went into the water, which is a real shame.
This guy used to compete against me, but when he was from China, now he's coaching in Malaysia and now he's allowed to compete for them.
So he's the grand old age of 30 years old, but he's still got it.
Pretty good.
Seven, seven point fives maybe.
Could be a little bit off the pace today.
Marks are, yeah, 7.5, two of them, and a seven.
So he opens up with a total of 68.20.
Now, great cheer to Jack Law, former European junior champion, made the final in Shanghai last year and acquits himself very well indeed.
Inward two and a half somersaults, 3.0 not too high tariff to start off with, that comes up later for Jack in the pike position.
Yeah, he's been diving well in training.
He won't be so pleased with that entry into the water.
He's playing safe a little bit here.
Jack does do the inward three and a half, but playing a game of tactics here, opening with an easier inward turn off.
He absolutely cruises it.
Just come out a little bit too early though.
The water brushing against the front side of his body.
He's only going to get 7.5s.
That will put him a little bit off the pace, but I'm very confident having watched him in training that he will feature as we go on.
Yeah, reasonable opening offer from Jack.
Sixty-six again, seven point fives and a seven will count all those marks with the line struck through will not count.
Remember, none of these marks carry through to the semis which will be on Tuesday morning, local time.
Now to
Well, Stefanos, probably one of the weakest divers in this contest.
He's going to really need to be on the top of his game to carry on through.
He's one of the younger generation of Greek divers.
So 22 years old.
He did very, very well to make these top 29 who are here today.
Just you see over a vertical.
Just staying in his shape a little bit too long as he goes into the water.
You can see the splash moving away.
Legs coming apart a little bit.
He'll get penalized for that.
There we go.
Quite heavily so as well.
Sixes from him.
54.00.
If he gets bored, he can always read his back.
D'Amato Rinaldi next up for Italy.
And two of the Italians are quite late in the program.
Last of the divers will be from Italy.
Inward two and a half somersaults.
Pike position difficulty 3.0 and another quite hirsute Italian today.
Oh, it looked a little bit tight to the diving board.
It's always tricky getting the distance correct on this inward movement.
You're standing backwards on your tiptoes.
You then need to swing your arms, jump up and away, but spin forwards towards the diving board.
He's OK.
I did move back a little bit, but he's OK.
Throwing up a little bit of splash.
Shame, really.
7.5s incoming, I would imagine.
Yeah, you've got to give it the clap.
7.5 and 7 for Rinaldi and that's okay not a bad start for him.
Qin Kai for China again just easing his way into the program no big starter for him back two and a half somersaults in the pike position.
Yeah, maybe the same as He Chong, He Chong.
Just playing a little bit safe.
3.0 to start the program.
I've seen it much better than this.
In training, it's much better.
This is actually, well, dare I say, for the Chinese standard, for King Kai's standard, mediocre.
I wouldn't give that more than an 8.
Maybe he'll sneak 8.5s because of his distinguished career and previous results list.
He's a little bit short of vertical.
It is very precise.
Let's see what the judges see.
Oh, they're a bit higher than I thought.
76.50, we have said before.
And then I will say again, the Chinese invariably are mocked up on their dives because of their reputations.
And maybe that was a case and a case in point there.
Troy Dumet will go with 3.1 so kind of betwixt in between in terms of the tariffs here on a forward three and a half somersaults with Pike second of the Americans to compete today.
Oh superb Troy the oldest competitor in this contest as is coach Matt Scoggin in Olympian himself
and absolutely drills the entry let's check this out here we go forward three and a half somersaults in the pike position now you see me now you don't what an entry this should get the first nines of the contest and quite right too troy you know achieving a lifetime dream of winning olympic medal earlier in the week
and uh wow well the americas are having a very good week i think inspired by the fact that greg lagard is here to mentor them and help them through and it seems to be working dividends through the course of the week he goes into third place troy domain after that dive as it is on our sheet of paper here with a forward two and a half somersaults two twists pike 3.4 big one
Oh, the crowd like that one, as you could imagine.
Some ooh-ing and ah-ing.
It's a pretty good dive from Yal.
I'll talk you through it as we go into the replay hurdle set.
On the end, a little bit back from the end, here's one and a half somersaults.
Here's the double twist.
Super quick on the double twist.
Yal's obviously normally all taped up.
He has terrible problems with ankle injuries, but today he looks apart from some on his toes.
He looks tape free, which is a good sign because this guy is an exciting diver.
And when he's on, he's on.
And he's on joint first after that.
It's a great difficulty helping him up to a total of 86.70 up there with Zakharov.
Very keen to get going here is Robert Pais Rodriguez of Venezuela.
Oh, he's done okay on the entry into the water.
Probably a little aggressive as he went in, so ankle heavily strapped there.
These guys on the springboard putting themselves through their paces, often receive injuries to all different parts of their body, but the ankles do take a kick and you're looking to get really, really strong legs.
Just skipping back from the diamond board there, a little bit aggressive on the way in.
Let's see what the judges think.
Well, they're going to give him my favorite mark of sixty-three.
All the sevens times three.
That's how you arrive at the total score for him.
Twenty-fifth place at the moment.
Of course, top eighteen go through.
Last of the divers in round one is another of the Italians just flexing those muscles.
Michele Bendetti in with two and a half with Pike.
Oh, beautiful dive from the Italian to finish up round one.
Mickey missed out in Athens.
Didn't make the Italian team.
And then again, in Beijing, it all looked good.
And then he missed out again.
So this was going to be his last-ditch effort to make the games.
He was absolutely thrilled to be on the team.
And that's opening up his campaign in fine style indeed.
Well done, Mickey.
Oh, Mickey, you're so fine.
You're so fine.
You blow my mind, hey, Mickey.
8.0.
And a total of seventy-two for Michele Bendetti.
End of round one.
And what a competitive round it was.
If that's only the prelims it is.
What the semis in the final are going to be like Huerta and Zakharov.
Joint top.
Working their way around down the board.
What a great start for Matthew Rosset in third place.
All of those will come to me through.
We stop right now as indeed most of them on this page will be.
Right down to the Malaysian in 18th.
As yet no sign of the Brits.
You have to wait for page number three for them but 68.2 is the qualification place and 67.50 for Chris Mears, 66 for Jack Law.
and at the bottom of Stavados, Vapourounas.
Probably won't be thinking about coming back from the semifinals at this stage, but there's still time to make up and repair the damage.
Great crowd in here again at the Aquatic Centre for the diving.
Very few spare seats.
17,500 or thereabouts crammed in here for every session of the diving.
They're here to support not just the Brits, but also the worldwide divers as well, like the Australian Ethan Warren.
The Australians need a bit of a boost at the moment after the week they've had in the Aquatic Centre.
Four and three and a half somersaults with Pike.
3.1 for his first second round dive.
for his first second round dive.
That's right.
Yeah, you threw me a little bit there.
I think you threw Ethan ever so slightly as well.
A little bit of a shaky start first round.
Second round, a little bit off the mark, just marginally.
But then diving comes down to margin.
Short as he went in.
Short vertical.
It still gets seven and a halves.
Maybe squeezing an eight.
But I've seen Ethan diving better than this.
Just letting go of his legs a little bit ambitiously, a little bit early.
But yeah, I think there might be his parents there.
Yeah, just to clarify, he is only doing one second round dive and that was it.
Seventy-two point eight five.
There's no repassage here or anything in diving.
You don't get a second chance to come back again in the same round.
Damien Seeley of France.
Nineteenth after round one.
This is a diving competition in case you think you have gone to the bodybuilding exercises.
In with three and a half somersault.
We took three point four.
Big degree of difficulty.
oh he's super strong well you can see how strong he is but he manages to use the board very well three meter springboard it's a lot about rhythm timing coordination strength power dynamic explosive nature anyway he's got it all going on he does make a little bit of a bodge on the end which is a real shame he did all the hard work and then he seems to go loose in the in his body as he went into the water look at this super slow motion see the divers parting their hands as they're trying to escape into the water with
absolutely no splash.
It almost gets away with it but not quite.
Uh sevens and six point five with the others discarded.
So, total when you multiply it by the degree of difficulty is sixty-eight for him.
Not expecting too many mistakes from the man in ninth place after round one.
Her Chong of China, world champion, Olympic champion, three World Series wins this year under his belt.
Four, two and a half
oh indeed the crowd are wooing and uh he won yesterday as he adjusts his uh his suit as he goes in there certainly no suit catastrophe as he went in the water beautiful dive look how high he is way above the five meter forward two and a half two twists he makes it looks like it's a walk in the park and i can assure you this is no walk in the park this is
one of the toughest dives that you can perform, and He Chong just makes it look like it's a beginner dive.
It makes it look as if you could do that, Bob.
Oh, yeah.
Well, funny, I was doing earlier today, but they didn't get me in the top 29, so I just missed out.
He Chong with 8.5s and 9s, and the briefest of briefs.
There is a Mark Suspension just up the way in case he runs out of underwear.
Evgeny Kuznetsov with a back three and a half somersaults.
Wow, we're up to three point five.
This is upping the stakes somewhat.
Oh, wow.
I don't know what to say.
If any is coming out and he's got nowhere to hide.
In fact, none of his competitors have got anywhere to hide.
If he carries on like this, he's going to be tough to keep up with even the two Chinese divers.
3.5 and he's buried it.
That's really good.
He'll get high 70s and I think he can do it even better than that.
Lots of taping down his back but obviously holding him together.
Good dive.
Afghani's coming out.
There's a revelation for you.
77 for the Russian which puts him in second place.
Daniel Arroyo of Mexico.
We are getting up into some high tariff dives here.
3.5 followed by a 3.4 forward two and a half somersaults, two twists in the pike position.
Oh, he almost got it down.
Little bit short as he went into the water.
Lots to fit in in this dive.
We've already seen it from Hur Chong just earlier in the round, who absolutely cruised it.
Daniel just showing us how difficult it is.
Lands on the end in good time.
Double twist, one and a half.
Oh, he just about scrapes it in.
It's good, though.
It's high degree of difficulty.
It'll get him over 70 points.
Wow.
And even the lower end of the field are diving well again.
There are some amazing performances today and some amazing dives and that was not bad.
Not quite in the eighth range but seven point fives and a seven.
German Stefan Fec wants to get on with it for three and a half.
oh here you go the first calamity oh oh my goodness it's silent in here sorry about that i think he's okay i can talk you through it what happened he landed on the end of the diving board and his foot completely slipped off the side he probably lost a toenail or two there
And therefore, look at this, slips off the side of the board, doesn't get in his pike chip, only has hold of one leg.
He looked a bit like the Isle of Man and then absolutely smacks himself like he'd just been slammed in wrestling.
And that is a failed dive.
Zeroes across the board.
Stephane Fek is out of it.
Yeah, he will not be back tomorrow because there's no marks attributed to that dive because he didn't complete the dive.
On to the Threlsmratjó of Venezuela.
Oh he had exactly the same dive he just watched his German counterpart there.
Absolute wow that doesn't happen very often but he just yeah really feel for him anyway the competition goes on there's still places to be fought for and this young man is trying to keep his head keep his cool other divers will be aware of that
Calamity that just took place with Stefan there and he's certainly out of it but this guy, he's still in it, the Venezuelan.
Well, that's the kind of mark that Stefan Feck would have liked to have seen against his name rather than zero zero zero zero.
Sixty-eight point two zero it is on that particular occasion.
Cesar Castro are Brazil for three and a half with Pike.
Yep, very tidy from Cesar.
Opened up with that beautiful first round dive.
Lower degree of difficulty.
Slowly starting to build now.
3.1 this one.
We've seen the previous three divers do this one.
Squeezing into the pike shape.
Just bending forward from the hip.
Keeping the legs straight.
He's tidy.
Maybe loses his feet a little bit as he goes in there.
This will get eight.
And that will keep him in the mix.
It is going to be so tight for those top 18 places.
I tell you, already it's developing into a contest where there will be few marks separating.
The time is around the 15 to 20 mark.
Kenny Yeoh of Malaysia for two and a half, two twists.
Oh, it's good.
Probably needed to come around a little bit more on the dive there to give the impression of being completely vertical.
Aerial work is good.
Here we are, squeezing into the pike, out.
Here's the double twist, maybe out a little bit early, leaving himself a little bit to do.
Marginally short, but that'll get eights.
If you're getting eights, you're going to go close to 80 points.
And if you're on 80 points, that's where exactly you need to be.
81.60 to be precise for Kenny Yeo.
And that will help his charge up the table quite a bit.
He's in third place now behind Chong and Kuznetsov.
Patrick Hausting hopes the same fate won't befall him as his German teammate.
Oh, it's a good dive.
Now, maybe the judges will see this or maybe it's just for us on the replay.
I think Patrick was a little bit twisted as he went in, landed on the corner of the diving board, still manages to do a good job.
You can see his head there just looking everywhere every somersault, but I can see both feet as he goes in, which means he's a little bit over twisted.
If any judges give him less than a seven, they would have seen that.
But of course, the judges do not get the replay.
No, they've missed it.
Lucky.
Yeah, he got away with that one.
And because of it, he's got 72.85, which will put him in the top five.
Alexei Plegorov of Ukraine, 3.8.
Stand by.
Forward, four and a half somersaults.
Oh, standby.
Hold on.
Take your hats off.
He did very well indeed.
Now the hurdle step, the approach to the end didn't do him any favors.
He had one foot slightly off the side of the board.
This is 3.8 and he just sneaks it in nicely.
He'll get sevens on that.
Look at where he lands.
And then he shoots forward.
That's way too far away from the diving board.
But wow, what a diver to be able to control that when your takeoff is medium to poor.
Wow.
Good work.
3.8.
Those marks along the bottom which they're not allowing on the screen for very long.
Sorry we can't take it all in but 83.6 it was.
We get on to Garcia.
Yeah good work from Javi.
Not waiting around, not giving us any time to go too much into the detail.
These dives are so difficult.
I don't know where to start.
Oh, he did lose his legs a little bit there.
That's very clear on the replay.
You probably wouldn't see that when you watch it for the first time.
Double twist, super slow-mo cam, just showing the strains on the divers.
Lots of photos on the internet of divers' faces close up mid-dive.
The slow motion giving you an impression.
That's good from Javi.
And 76.50.
Smile on the face of Chris Colwell.
The divers really enjoying themselves here, enjoying themselves in competition and obviously hoping that they're going to be returning for the semi-finals in about 14 hours time.
Forward three and a half somersaults with Pike for Colwell.
3.1 degree of difficulty.
Amir Bagatel compared to that 3.8.
Yeah, 3.1, but if you're going to execute it with that much precision, it's going to work for you.
Kristi Nipson there, bronze medalist in the three meter synchro, supporting his teammate here, Chris, doing a beautiful job.
Quite tall for a dive up, so he looks very elegant as he's spinning around in the shapes.
Little back from the end, but that's straight up and down.
That'll get eight and a halfs.
It's a good dive.
Yeah, anything in the mid 70s and higher is a good dive.
And as we get 75.95 for Colwell, we have an impressive start from Matteo Rossi of France, can he back it up 3.4 degree of difficulty on this inward three and a half somersaults with tuck.
Oh, he can't back it up.
I think he just piled, well, the commentator's curse right there, Bob.
Opening round dive.
Put him in the top, what, top four?
Where was he after the first round?
Incredible.
Now, just showing you how difficult these dives are.
Very easy to get lost, get confused.
Spinning around so quickly.
Your eyes are being pulled back.
Loads of G-forces.
What a shame, because the aerial work was fantastic, and oh, see ya.
Yeah, has a chat with his coach, but you can't get that one back, I'm afraid.
Fours and four point five that really has dented his chances of returning tomorrow.
But after that first round dive still has a decent chance.
Francois Imboul Dulac for Canada.
A new kind of raw recruit really to Canadian diving.
Four, three and a half somersaults with pike three point one, the degree of difficulty attached to this one.
Oh, he ended up okay in the end.
I don't know whether you saw the same thing as me as he came into the end.
I wasn't sure which direction he was going to end up facing in.
Seemed to drift a little bit in the air like it was windy.
Anyway, he got it together in the end.
Forward three and a half, piked.
You know, he's not as dynamic or as strong as some of the other divers, so he's never going to get more than a seven, 7.5.
He's not finishing the dive high enough.
but still 21 years old.
Where was he going?
He was going sideways.
It did seem that way.
Marks are okay.
Not overly impressive for him.
65.10.
That's going to take a little bit of a dent in terms of his position in the table.
Inia Zakharov back three and a half somersaults.
3.5.
oh super smooth now these medals are going to be highly contested and they've got a long way to go yet but if you're a betting man or lady and you're watching this this guy is worth a punt
Beautiful dive.
This is so tricky.
3.5.
That's going to get way over 80 points.
Wow.
He's putting the pressure on the Chinese.
Well, he was second in Shanghai.
He split the Chinese last year, because they were one and three.
And he was second in Shanghai.
And the way he started here, you would not bet around him not being in that position again.
84 and two very solid dives.
86.7 and 84 to start with.
Reverse 2 and 1.5, 1 and 1.5 twist.
Alexander Deputty.
Oh, just showing his skill.
Landing way back from the end of the diving board.
I shifted back in my chair.
I wasn't happy.
Look at that.
Way back from the end.
Has to reach up and over the diving board.
If he wasn't so skilled, he'd have been a lot closer to the diving board there.
Of course, a few weeks ago, hitting his head on the diving board on a different dive to this one.
Anyway, safe distance away in the end.
It's only going to get seven and a halfs.
It's OK.
It's OK. Long way to go.
Yeah, 7.5 for Alex.
perhaps still not quite in the um the shape we normally expect to see him in terms of his quality of diving.
3.3 degree of difficulty on that.
So uh it will help him a little bit bit of a buffer.
That 3.8 dive again.
The big tariffs early from the Ukraine and Russia.
Ford four and a half.
Oh, nice.
Nice.
Very good, Kavasha.
Wow.
I wish I could describe to you how difficult this dive actually is because the two you've seen so far have been absolutely spot on.
Forward four and a half, hanging on to those shins, bending at the ankles and at the knees, just squeezing into that tight ball.
This could get 90 points.
That's absolutely stunning.
What a dive.
Obviously the tape helping.
I need to get some tape on.
Yeah, you do.
But make sure it's the right tape this time, please.
91.20 for Kavasha and he goes into second place behind Zakharov and they really are front loading their dives here.
The high tariffs early on giving them the early advantage as Castaneda.
Yeah, he's looking to get rid of his dives, not get rid of them.
So, I get them done very very quickly as soon as the referee gives you permission.
Away you go.
forward three and a half in the pike position.
It's tough to follow such a big scoring dive.
It'll get Sevens.
I don't think Sevens is going to cook it in this kind of competition.
Sevens it is and that gives you a total of 65.10 for Castaneda.
which Mia is enjoying this preamble, prelude if you like to his second round dive which is a reverse two and a half somersaults with Pike just on the cusp of qualification after round one, three more, four more rounds after this.
Nice, really, really good.
I was listening to the crowd as there's Tom Daley, Sarah Barrow, Peter Waterfield, all of them here to support their teammates.
Chris Mears, only 19 years old, beautiful reverse turn off, needed it, needs to go over 70 points and that will.
holding his nerve, smiling, enjoying this occasion, inspired by performances so far into the hot tub to keep warm and then straight back out into the cool off area.
Good, good, good, good.
Three eights, seventy-two.
He'll be happy with that and that will move him up the table by a mark or two and a position or two as well.
Malaysia back two and a half.
Oh just a little bit off his game as short as he entered the water.
A real work was okay I think he just came out of the dive a little bit too ambitiously a little bit too early which will cost him he'll only get sevens there we are just needed to hang on a little bit longer then the water wouldn't have smacked him on the back of the legs as he went in
There we go.
Next up, Jack Law.
I can already hear the crowd shouting and cheering.
Let's give you the marks, though, for Huang first.
And here's Total, as I take it off the screen for you.
Well, 63 exactly.
Now, this man's hero is Usain Bolt.
How inspired will he be by what he saw on the track last night, Jack Law?
Pretty inspired.
Looks a little shaky out there for Jack.
He's got so much home support.
Yeah, I've seen it better than this.
He's right on the corner of the diving board.
He does really well not to end up in the middle of the pool doing a Steven feck, but he manages to hang on there even with a poor takeoff.
Look at the strain and effort going into this one and a half twist into the one and a half twist into the two and a half somersaults.
He squares it up nicely on the end, but that was a poor takeoff.
Well done, Jack.
Stay in with it.
Sevens and seven point five.
It's going to put him right around the eighteen or nineteen position.
Twenty-nine and I played at the bottom and likely to remain there unless things improve greatly.
For three and a half.
Oh, beautiful entry into the water.
We're talking about the rip entry and that was an ideal example of one.
Punching a water with a flat hand, ripping the hands aside as he goes in.
Almost causing a vacuum just to disappear as he went in.
Good work from the young Greek diver.
Well, of course, he can't finish bottom because that will go to Stefan Fek after that failed dive, so he will have moved up a position anyway.
In fact, he's moved up a few positions thus far.
Up to 21st to Vanos Paparounas of Greece.
Now on to Tommaso Rinaldi, first of the two talents.
I think you're done with that interruption, sir.
Thank you very much.
Forward three and a half somersaults with pike, 3.1, the degree of difficulty.
Tommaso unfazed by the peculiar shouting coming from an audience member.
Divers, as soon as the whistle is blown by the referee, that is the sign to the audience to keep stum.
And someone decided to shout but Tommaso unfazed by it.
The dive's okay.
It's, well, it's good actually but in this level of competition, it goes down to okay.
Sevens, seven point fives.
Yep, sevens it will be.
Times the degree of difficulty, three point one.
Those marks on your left with the line struck through do not count towards the total score.
I'm sure you know that by now but we get new viewers all the time who need to know that.
Forward two and a half somersaults, two twists for Chin Kai of China.
Oh, it's very good.
It's tidy.
It's precise.
Chinkai not looking like his former self, I must admit.
The Russians are certainly taking it to him.
And I think that that might move him up a little bit from seventh.
But not a whole lot.
It's good.
It'll get eights.
In fact, it is a very good dive.
But this first round dive left him off the case a little bit.
Off the pace and off the case.
Not sure.
It's going to be a long competition.
It could be a very briefcase, actually.
He's diving like that, but it'll be all right for the semifinals.
I'm sure all right for the final as well.
85 for Ching Kai.
Again, maybe overmarked a little bit there, but that's the way the judges saw it.
Troy Dumay got to a very good start.
Can he back it up?
3.3 degree of difficulty on this reverse.
Two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists, performed in the pike position.
Oh, unwavering.
Yes, he can back it up.
Yeah, very, very solid.
All about consistency.
And Troy Demay is certainly displaying that out here today.
Obviously on a high for winning an Olympic medal last week.
And so he should be eights, 8.5s.
Will it get 80 points?
If it does, he'll certainly be very much up in the business end of the field after round two.
Nothing to clarify for you.
If you saw the women's on the previous couple of days, then you may have seen five rounds.
The women's is five.
The men's is six.
So we'll be halfway at the end of the next round.
Round three.
We're in round two.
We're well into round two now.
Yehiel Castillo Huerta of Mexico, in with three and a half somersaults with Tuck.
Joint leader after the first round.
Yep that's going to keep him certainly in the top half of the field and that's what it's all about this morning 3.4 degree of difficulty just maybe moving his hips back a little bit before he takes off so he's just a little low on the water but you're looking for that vertical entry and anything close to 80 points is exactly what you're looking for
and I'm sure y'all will be there.
Yeah, they like it.
They're they're the coaches.
Eighty-one point six zero and that will keep him right close to the top if not quite at the top anymore.
He's in second place by Ilya Zakharov.
Rodriguez four and three and a half with Pike three point one.
Where's he going on that board?
Yeah, he's certainly going in the wrong direction to start with.
He seemed to place his first foot very close to the end and then drift backwards.
That's obviously a slight error, but he manages to look way back from the end of the springboard.
That's not very springy back there.
You need to be right on the end, obviously not over the end.
We see what happens when, you know, you've got your feet over the end of the diving board.
Anyway, Robert survives.
Let's see what marks he gets.
Had me a little worried again there.
That's almost another calamity waiting to happen.
6.5s across the board.
60.45.
Not going to help him a great deal.
Kelly Bendetti wants to go and he is going.
Oh, it's beautiful entry into the water.
A little bit of short vertical as he goes in.
Mickey would have wanted to, yeah, he's warming up his legs to go there.
Here we are.
Here's the replay.
Squeezing into the pike shape.
Oh, just crimping his knees slightly there to make the rotations a little bit easier.
That's actually a little bit off where he needed to be.
He's right on the corner as well.
It's so tricky as a springboard diver to land on the end of the diving board, it seems, this evening.
They're going in all kinds of directions, aren't they?
I wonder if they've all been in the pub before this one.
I doubt it very much.
Somebody put goose grease on the end of the board or something.
It was slipping off.
It's amazing what's happened in this competition thus far.
We've only had two rounds and four more still to come.
Ilya Zakharov, what a start from him.
Watch that, boy.
He could be very, very dangerous indeed.
Already is.
Yahel Castillo Huerta, Gavasha of Ukraine.
Ukraine, three and four.
USA, five.
Chinese, six and seven.
That's a surprise.
Chris Mears has snuck into the top 18 as has Jack Law.
So Jack Law stays there in four rounds time.
He and Chris Mears will be progressing into the semifinals.
And these on the last page, have either got too much to do or might as well forget it, including Stefan Fek.
Sadly, it's what, 60 points adrift of everybody else after that failed second round dive.
It's been a very intriguing and entertaining competition so far.
A few little twists and turns that we weren't expecting and the Chinese further down the pecking order than we had imagined.
That's because some people have front loaded their dives here with very big tariffs.
That's right.
The Chinese still have their highest degrees of difficulty still to come.
And of course, it's about six dives and not two.
So let's say a third of the way through.
Big third round dive for Ethan Warren.
It's a three point eight.
It's a forward four and a half.
A lot of risk, but a lot of points attached if he gets this right.
Oh yes well it seems to be the evening that everyone is giving their forward four and a half a good show and Ethan Warren needed a good one little bit off the pace after his first two dives this is his biggest dive his most difficult dive and he certainly slots it in beautifully
eighty-six, eighty-seven, eighty-eight, keep going, keep going, keep going, keep going.
There you go.
89.30 and he was 19th after round two.
That will do him a great deal of good and should move him up quite a few places as well.
Now, Dami and Celie are France forward three and a half.
Not quite as
Yeah opting for the slightly easier forward so forward three and a half only carries a 3.1 but it's much less riskier than the 3.8 we saw previously.
Salman doing a good job there.
Lots of people asking on Twitter why there's three diving boards there.
Well there's a lot of divers competing and so when you've got
you know 30 girls and 40 boys all training at the same time to have three diving boards to choose from actually it eases the congestion all the diving boards are three meters they should all be made of the same you know ingredients so to speak or duraflex spring boards so it's just divers preference
Sixty-nine point seven five for Demi and Sidi and that will maybe help him a bit out of his current predicament of being twenty-second.
Now, you don't often see the Chinese in sixth place but that's where He Chong, the world champion is, of course.
Don't worry.
He won't worry because he got two more rounds provided he gets through this one semifinal and a final to come.
Top eighteen to qualify.
He's in sixth.
Here's his reverse.
Three and a half somersaults with Tuck.
Oh, it's a big dive from her Olympic champion four years ago.
And of course, he's not bothered really, you know, he's in sevenths after the second round.
He knows that he will be steadfast and consistent throughout.
And so that is just an example.
I don't know whether it's worth a nine, but it will get eight, eight and a half.
So it's a big dive and that will shoot him up the leaderboard.
nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine, nine,
That could make it more difficult for the Russian here, lands on the end of the diving board, into the tuck shape, all looks good so far.
Reverse three and a half, just kicks up two high, and now it's time to get your surfboards out.
Surf's up, what a shame.
He could do something like goose grease now, couldn't he?
Yeah, this is yeah, this is going to make it difficult.
I think he's got a good buffer.
He's going to have to dig deep.
Forty-five.
That's going to hurt, isn't it?
Big time.
Forty-five.
Well, he's going to go shooting down the rankings.
He was eighth after dive two.
He might find himself struggling for qualification after this round if everybody dives the way they have been.
Daniel O'Rourke of Mexico back two and a half with Pike currently in 19th place.
Oh, tipping over a vertical there as he went in.
Only 3.0.
A few of the divers opting to use this.
Worth mentioning that the divers have to go in different directions.
Six dives and five groups of dive.
Forward, backwards, which is what you're looking at here.
Inwards, which is where you stand backwards, spin forwards.
Reverse is where you walk down the diving board, jump away from it and spin backwards towards it.
And the twist group.
And then you also get another option.
Divers here today doing six dives, five different groups.
Hopefully that explains some of the intricacies.
Well, this round's proving to be a bit eventful, maybe catastrophic for some of the divers, a 45 followed by a 54.
now Stefan Fek is getting great encouragement after that dropped dive completely missed dive in round two so he is not going to qualify but here's his forward two and a half with two twists yeah it's really good to see he had almost a standing ovation then you can see his teammates there knowing that it takes a lot of courage to carry on it's all over for Stefan his olympic
dreams are as good as over because this is his only event and unfortunately with that failed second round dive that it's impossible for him to make it through to the semifinals so he's diving it out now it's a long way I'm sure he just wants to get it over with but he's showing you know his courage and his professionalism and he's carrying on.
Six point fives across the board as we get Contreras Bracho who doesn't hang around for anybody least of all me four two and a half two twists
Yeah, no hang time there for Bracho either.
He's a little bit low on the water.
It's a big dive.
It's 3.4.
This is his most complicated or one of his most complicated dives.
He needs to be on the end of the diving board there to give himself half a chance.
So it's average.
Well, averagely good.
So I guess sevens.
Maybe, yeah, maybe, maybe not a little bit scruffy.
I don't know.
Let's see.
I don't think the judges know either.
Look at that.
Six up to seven.
They weren't quite sure either.
Sixty-six point three.
That's two very low tariff, not low tariff, but low scoring dives together.
Now, Cesar Castro, can you change all that with a forward two and a half somersaults, two twists, pike three point four.
He always seems to lose his feet as he goes into the water.
It was a busy dive.
He didn't have a lot of time, but it's really neat and tidy.
He's hanging ten, all ten toes over the end of the diving board.
Manages to complete the dive, but let's have a look here as he goes in.
You can see his feet split, so maybe the judges are penalizing him, or maybe it happened so quickly that they didn't see it.
We'll wait and see.
He did very well there with his toes all the way over the end.
I've got to say the best judging has always been in the final this week when we're down to the best judges in fewer countries.
But 7.5 gives him a 76.50 with the multiplication of that degree of difficulty.
Back at the Olympics for the second time after 12 years, Ken Iino.
Yeah, nice work from Ken Iino.
Very elegant diver and yeah, he's performing consistently well today.
That's him.
Was he in the top 10?
He was, yes, top 10 after the first two rounds.
Beautiful third round dive halfway through his contest and he's certainly where he wants to be in striking distance of the semi-final spots.
Well, others are faltering, but he isn't.
And a good series of dives, 71, followed by an 81, followed by a 72.
And after an absence of 12 years, his return to the Olympics has been pretty good so far.
Patrick Housding in 12th, forward two and a half, two twists.
Yes, very solid.
Watching his teammate having a tough day at the office.
It's down to Patrick now to represent Germany and get through.
And he is a very, very good diver.
And I would be surprised to see him not go through.
And that's three out of three for housing so far.
That could squeeze over 80 points.
It's 3.4.
It's good.
Joe's just inputting into their machines, coming up on the scoreboard in front of us and then in front of the viewers at home.
81.60 for Housding.
12th in Shanghai, the World Championships last year.
Here comes Alexei Prigorov with his back two and a half, so it's 3.0.
It's his easiest dive, only 3.0, opting to play a little bit safer than some of his other high risk dives.
And yeah, he's plopped it on his head.
It's not going to get more than seven and a halfs or eights, but it's where he needs to be.
squeezing into the pike shape.
Moving back a little bit from the diving board, causing a few discrepancies with the control into the hot tub and a little wave for us at home.
67.50, might have wanted a bit more than that, but it is a low degree of difficulty, so probably worth about that.
Javier Ilana Garcia, four and three and a half somersaults, pike 3.1.
Oh, that's almost there for Harvey.
Just a little bit off his game.
Again, entering the water short.
You'll see on the replay.
You're looking for that vertical entry in.
Harvey not quite hanging on to his shape long enough.
Just let's go a little bit early.
Little shorter vertical.
He hoped for a bit more.
He'd get eights.
and he was in fourteenth after the second round.
Yeah.
So, he's certainly going to get through to the semis if he continues to stay in that region.
Seventh at the moment.
You know, obviously, he dropped down a few more notches yet but at the moment, he's got a little bit of daylight between himself and the Strugglers.
Now, Chris Colwell gives us a big smile every
Dives, here comes his third round attempt on a forward two and a half somersaults and two twist pike, worth 3.4 with the degree of difficulty.
Yeah, it's good.
Chris has back loaded his list.
So this is where he starts to bring out his big guns.
So this is a first of his three point fours in succession.
So here we are.
Lands on the end.
Beautiful hurdle step.
Such great rhythm and timing.
That's very precise.
It will be squeezing high 70s, maybe even 80 points out of that dive.
That's exactly where he needs to be.
Yeah, anything 80 plus is always good and is right on the cusp of an 80.
79.90 for Colwell lifts him up to third.
Now this man started like a train.
This is a huge dive and this could be the difference between him qualifying and not.
Forward four and a half somersaults for Rosset in the tuck position.
Here we go.
He could be the comeback king.
He's just got his claws out and he's started to haul himself back into contention.
A beautiful first round dive, an absolutely diabolical second round dive and then he's nailed his most difficult one.
3.8, the forward four and a half somersaults in the tuck position.
Wow, here we go.
Well, that's a good recovery.
Very, very good recovery from Rossi.
Seven point fives times that degree of difficulty gives him uh mid eighty-fives.
So, a reparation job has started one and truly for the Frenchman.
Let's move on to the young Canadian, Francois Imboul Dulac.
Twenty-third after round two.
Need to make up some ground back.
Two and a half somersaults with Pike.
Three point zero
Yeah, he's nice and steady today, Francois.
He certainly will probably be one of the ones that doesn't quite make the cut.
But if he stays there and other people are faltering, he could certainly sneak up into top 18.
I think he was in the early twenties after, has a rank after that second round.
That'll probably keep him about that place after his third round.
The mark is sixty-three.
It's sevens but it was a low degree of difficulty.
So our favorite mark returns again.
Where it gone?
Missing it.
Sixty-three for Imboudulak.
Now Ilya Zakharov first after round two.
First after round one.
Reverse three and a half.
Oh, he sneaked it in there.
I did actually move towards Bob there, not because I wanted to get closer to Bob, but because I thought Zakhov was a little bit close to the diving board there.
Actually, when he goes by, he's OK. Let's have a look.
He's okay.
He didn't want to do a Greg Luganis and fortunately Greg Luganis, of course, world and Olympic champion, his head in dramatic fashion on a reverse dive in the 88 games.
No Greg Luganis for Zakharov today, but that's good.
82 points in the lead.
82.25 and Greg is mentoring a lot of the USA divers here.
Now Alex reversed two and a half somersaults with Pike for Depati.
Very interesting indeed, Departee playing it safe normally doing the reverse three and a half which is what we saw from Zakharov playing safe here with a 3.0 so it needed to be very good and it was just that beautiful you could just see that technique this should get nines and it needs to get nines because beautiful slow motion look at that looking at where he's been spotting moving his chin looking at the water leaving his toes towards the scoreboard and then he goes all in less than 1.8 seconds
Well, he knows how to do it.
Does Alex, twice a silver medalist at the Olympics, hasn't quite got the demeanor I'd like to see from Alex at the moment.
He kind of has that slightly hangdog look.
Hopefully that will return, the smile will return anyway in the semifinals.
Reverse two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists for India Kavasha.
Yeah, Kavasha's nailing his dives, slotting them in.
And that's exactly what he needs to do.
Dive after dive.
That's three out of three for Kavasha.
Big degrees of difficulty as well.
He's not messing around.
Probably his fifth round dive is his lowest degree of difficulty.
But at the moment, he's very much in the mix.
How much in the mix is he?
79.20 puts him for the time being at least into third place.
Looking fairly comfortable for qualification, though we're not even halfway yet.
Remember, three more rounds still to come.
Here's the young Colombian, Sebastian Villar Gastoneda.
Forward two and a half somersaults, two twists, 3.4.
Yeah, just a little bit low on the water.
You can certainly see the difference between some of the stronger divers.
Here we are, the young Colombian.
He does a good job.
Here's a double twist after the one and a half somersaults.
Here's the completion of the dive.
Just running out of room.
He probably won't get more than sixes on that one.
Just showing you how difficult these dives are.
68 for Sebastian via Gastaneda and doesn't appear on my front page.
It's quite a long way down at the moment, in fact.
And just in 14th place.
Listen to that roar.
17 and a half thousand people, the majority of which
are favoring the Brits.
Chris Mears learning the lessons previous divers have had, taking his time and just soaking up the atmosphere before he gets his full concentration on a reverse.
Two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists, 3.3 degree of difficulty.
Mears currently 15th after round two.
Oh, just a little bit short as he goes in, but the crowd like it.
They're ripping the roof off here.
There's Chris's mum and dad.
Avid supporters of their son.
Here we are swinging the arms.
One and a half twists into the two and a half somersaults.
Just a little shorter vertical.
That means, well, you'll struggle to get more than sevens, which
Oh, that moving down the path.
Yeah, you can hear the booze already.
You haven't seen the market.
So, wait, we'll not spoil your surprise.
Six point fives.
Can I boo?
I'm not allowed to do that.
It's fairly unprofessional.
Like I normally am, really.
Kian Huang, Malaysia.
Reverse two and a half, somersaults one and a half.
Twist.
You can put it home if you, of course, if you want to.
Oh, following me is with the same dive.
3.3 degree of difficulty.
So it's big, it's tricky.
Here we are, here's the one and a half twist, moving safely away from the diving board.
Little bit scruffy, it's a better effort than Chris Mears, probably gonna get 7.7.5.
Steady, from the 30 year old from Malaysia, formerly China.
There are times when Leon gets a little bit personal, sorry, probably big and tricky again, but never mind, it does happen from time to time.
Now to Jack Law.
again the crowd responds lots of union flags and that's the 10 meter ball we'll see later on in the week and go down seven meters you'll find jack law the final rung of qualifications reversed three and a half somersaults with
Oh he's right over the end of the diving board hanging ten and that's not good especially when you need to stay in balance spin backwards look at this hanging ten he did well to stay on skips off the diving board just showing how talented this young boy is he's only 17 he's really young in the competition squeezing into that tuck shape as tight as he possibly can waiting oh
Oh, this is going to be tough for Jack Knife.
It is going to be very tough indeed when you get marks like that.
Oh dear, dear, dear.
Five point fives and that is going to be a big dent in terms of qualification.
Not completely irreversible but it's going to be tough now.
Mears is doing quite well.
Jack Law is just not quite on his game at the moment.
Well, in the second round, here's his third round dive.
Oh, it's another tidy dive.
Beautiful entry into the water.
Maybe his aerial work isn't quite as impressive or as strong as some of the divers, but you can certainly see why he's earned his spot here in the Olympic Polymeries.
Superb entry into the water.
Splashless.
7.5s, I think so.
Well his reaction really works in a very, very poor opening round dive.
But he has since recovered very, very well indeed.
7.5s, good total, 76.50.
Now to the first of the Italians.
Here's Tommaso Rinaldi.
Are they back?
Two and a half somersaults with Pike.
25th after round two but a couple of people have faltered just above him.
There's a chance for the first of the two Italians we'll see to move up a few spaces.
Yes he will.
Yes, he will indeed.
Beautiful dive.
3.0 needed to be good.
It's all about being consistent.
Seeing some divers starting to falter now.
Tommaso there.
One of his better efforts today.
Will he get 70 points?
I don't think he'd be too far away.
Hear that heartbeat in the background.
Quite dramatic here in the pool.
Well, I don't think we need any more drama.
I think we've had plenty of drama.
Thank you very much.
Please.
More drama.
I think you could cope with it.
I can cope with it.
So Rinaldi with that marked him now.
Ching Kai of China.
Seventh after round two.
Here comes a big one from him.
Three point five reverse three and a half.
Oh, it's a big dive indeed.
3.5, it's the one that we just saw Jack Law make a bit of a mess of, but no mistakes from Chin Kai here, landing on the end of the diving board, up and away, way above the five meter, and then drops into the water, making it look easy.
Will he get 90 points?
Maybe.
very close to just shy of eight point fives for Jinkai but that's left him up to second place.
Zakharov though holding firm in first.
Troy Dumet was in
Fifth place after round two.
So very comfortable in terms of looking forward to qualification for the semis.
Back two and a half somersaults with Pike, the man from the USA.
3.0 degree of difficulty on his third round dive.
Yeah, this is a dive that Troy used to start with, maybe a little bit shaky for him at the beginning, seems to have moved it to the middle of his program.
It's his lowest degree of difficulty, so it needs to be good.
And that's a good effort from Demay there.
I've not seen him diving this well for many, many years.
In fact, he's in the form of his life.
and he's 32 years old, which of course isn't very old for everyone at home, but in diving terms, it's getting on a bit.
That's how I make me feel.
Positively ancient.
It makes me feel positively ancient.
I've got to tell you that much.
Thank you very much.
76.50 for Troy Dumais.
If you don't mind, Grandad will introduce the next diver now.
It's a 3.8.
Yeah, we've seen this before.
We've seen it go right.
We've seen it go wrong.
A forward four and a half summer sorts with tuck for the Mexican.
Oh, and I think that's somewhere in between.
Somewhere in between right and wrong.
It's good and it certainly will keep Yael in contention.
It's high risk.
It's good to see him using it here in the polymerase, not hiding, using all his big dives.
Forward, four and a half.
Look at the strain on his face hanging on there for, well, for dear life, but that's worthwhile.
Worth, look at the face.
There you go.
Careful.
I know.
forward four and a half.
So impressive and it's good.
It'll get more 80 points.
Will it?
Let's see.
If you think about taking a restraining order on him for some time.
Yeah, Castillo Huerta comes up with eighty-one point seven zero.
What danger money if he keeps doing that.
Now, on to uh Rodriguez, Robert Pais Rodriguez of Venezuela Pike position for his back two and a half.
Oh, they're all diving.
It's a great reaction.
Oh, well, it was all right, you know.
So when you're comparing contrasting with the best in the world, you can see here he's only 18, Robert Rodriguez.
And you can see it's a little bit here and there, a little bit scruffy.
It turns in.
He doesn't quite turn into a banana, but he does the impression of a banana on the end there, loses his legs a little bit.
Of course, the judges don't see the replay, but they did pick up on those discrepancies.
49.50.
Not a great mark, not a great succession of scores and he will be struggling to return in the semi-finals.
On to Michele Bendetti.
Take a little bit more time, a bit more considered over this dive because the last one he rushed into very quickly.
Back two and a half somersaults this time for his third round dive.
Sixteenth after round two.
This one in the pike position.
Nice, really nice third round dive there.
Completing this third round from Italy, Michele Benedetti.
3.0, so it needed to be good, and that's very good.
Bag full of eights, and he'll certainly shift himself up the rankings a little bit with that one, especially with quite a few divers faltering on round three, halfway.
Yep, halfway, three done, three more to go, and Bendetti picks up 72.
Three eights multiplied by the degree of difficulty.
So now we change the judges.
And we look at the score at halfway.
And Ilya Zakharov, impeccable so far in first place.
Chinese two and four.
Kuwait is having a good time.
As one of the Americans is doing well.
So both Americans on that front page.
Only one German now in contention.
Now, what's happening on page two?
Alexander Departee has moved into a position to qualify.
As has nearly the Greek there.
Nineteenth place.
Good recovery by Paparounas.
But you don't see the British flag on there, do you?
Because Chris Mears is twenty-first.
Jack Law is twenty-sixth.
Chris not that far away.
Jack quite some way away.
You'll have to really pick up his game.
Last three dives to have any chance of qualification.
Stefan Fek, sadly, well and truly out of it after dropping round two.
New judges in place.
Always clap themselves.
We'll be the judge of that.
Thank you very much.
At the end of your three rounds.
Well, I think it's important that the judges are changed.
It's a long, long competition, and everyone gets tired, including you and I, Bob.
So we need to hold our concentration.
But when you're judging dive after dive after dive after dive after dive, you get a bit tired.
So mix out the judges, fresh panel.
The divers obviously remain the same, halfway.
They don't get a break, do they?
Well, they get a break in between.
The judges have to judge every dive.
The divers have to do one dive every round.
That's a great shot.
That's a really great shot from the 10-meter board.
You'll be seeing that a lot more towards the end of the week when we have the women's 10-meter and the men's, which people keep asking me, when is it?
It's on Friday.
The preliminaries and the semifinals are on Saturday morning.
That's UK time, of course, wherever you're watching in the world.
And the final is at 7 o'clock British summertime on Saturday evening.
Now, Ethan Warren, first diver in round four, in the comfort zone at the moment, in tenth, in with three and a half somersaults with tuck, 3.4, kind of a middling dive, but with still plenty of danger attached to it.
This is definitely not a middling dive.
3.4 degree of difficulty.
This is as tough as it comes on the inward move.
Got to stay right over the diving board, squeezing into the tuck shape.
Got to stay close enough to make it, but jump far enough away to miss it.
You can see him almost landing on his chamois there, which is what the divers used to dry themselves off.
Obviously using that as a little bit of a spotting technique.
He's on his head again.
It's okay, and it's a big score because of the degree of difficulty.
76.50 thumbs up and a smile from Ethan and for the time being he moves into first.
Now we've seen a bit of a cure at stake performance by Damian Sealy so far.
Let's see what his reverse three and a half somersaults with tuck is like.
It's worth 3.5 on the DD.
Oh he's done okay with it.
He did kind of turn his body towards us as he came into the end of the diving board.
I'm not quite sure
why he did that or how come as you can see just facing slightly skew if but not too skew if for the judges to penalize he's moving sideways a lot actually let's see if we get an overhead shot you have to take it for me he was moving sideways which will impact the entry into the water just drifting as he goes in we call that cast in diving and there we are cast in fishing as well don't they
Sounds like I know what I'm talking about.
I haven't got a clue what I'm talking about quite frankly but there you go.
Wouldn't be the first time.
He Chong of China in with three and a half somersaults with tuck three point four and um I like about the Chinese and like some of the other dives we've seen today they are studied and very methodical in the way they do things.
They don't rush into a dive.
They take all the time that's allowed to them.
He's fourth after round three.
Well, that is still very, very good, but I'm a little surprised it was as splashy on the entry as we saw there from He Chong.
Normally drilling his entries with such precision.
And this one, he's attempting to empty the pool.
Well, maybe empty the pool is a little bit harsh, but he's throwing up much more splash than we're used to.
So he might struggle to get eights on that.
He did all the hard work and then just letting the dive go over.
Yeah.
He's just not happy.
Not happy with that.
Not happy her.
What what do we think?
8 and 7.5 about right for that?
7.5 more than eight.
Definitely.
Okay.
Well, one of the eights will count as we move on to Afghani because nets off.
Forward two and a half.
Two twists.
Three point four.
Oh, he's going to get his dig his heels in.
He dig his toes in actually and start getting back up this field.
Twenty-second.
Is he twentieth
third round.
I've let him down.
This one will help.
They'll probably get sevens but I would have imagined why he definitely needs more than sevens to to make his comeback.
Could we see an upset happening?
Team GB with some work to do and Russian number two with some work to do still.
20th after round three that would not improve the situation as everybody else
screws up on their dive.
Let's see what we can get from the Mexican.
Who's next up?
Daniel Aro.
Reverse three and a half.
Well, it's the biggest dive for the young Mexican.
Just a shame really.
He managed to get the
in the right place all he needed to do was push his feet up a little bit higher as he entered the water let's have a look here just let's go a little bit early turns into a bit of a banana back and goes into the water sixes
shame really because he did all the hard work and then just miss miss yeah miscalculated his exit from the dive and gets for his pains it might have been quite painful that one 68.25 that's not going to help him he was 27th before that is going to move up a great deal after that
Well, let's see how the crowd reacts to the next man on the board, Contreras Bracho of Venezuela, because he's in that kind of territory with Chris Mears and Jack Law in particular at the moment.
Back two and a half somersaults with Pike for the Venezuelan.
Well, if you if you're expecting Stephen Feck, he's obviously pulled out of the competition because we've just skipped a diver.
Confused me for a few seconds, but now we've moved on to the Venezuelan.
So Stephen Feck, who failed the dive, obviously suffered a bit of an injury when he slipped off the diving board in dramatic fashion and he's at the Venezuelan there back two and a half in the pike position.
Pretty middle of the road.
Sevens, but he's still performing consistently.
It's only twenty one.
Marks are as follows.
All the lines through those marks do not count, so the sevens all do.
And we have sixty-three.
Just to confirm for you, to confuse me for a bit as well, that seven feck is no longer in this competition.
He's gone but Cesar Castro very much in it with his back two and a half somersaults, twelfth after round three.
Yep.
It's okay from the Cesar.
This is lowest degree of difficulty.
So it needed to be good.
3.0.
It's got a couple of low DDs in there as we call them.
And this is one of them.
A couple more to follow actually.
Finishing his list with his, all of his dives, a little bit basic, which always makes it difficult for him to get in unless of course he's diving consistently, which he is.
I expect him to continue to do that and to sneak through into the semi-final.
yeah more than sinking at the moment but there's plenty of divers still to go third place for him now Keniyo of Malaysia he's having a good day and 11th after round three oh he continues to have a good day and this is what it's all about dive after dive consistency you can see lots of divers faltering
And the divers who are the ones who continue to focus on the job continue to land upright on their heads just like Kenny's doing there for us.
High 70s for that diver I would imagine.
3.3 degree of difficulty.
Good work Kenny.
Well, I've got to say, 71 followed by an 81, followed by a 72, followed by a 79.20.
We've had some consistent performers in the competition so far and he's certainly up there amongst them.
Patrick Housding, comfortable top ten at the moment, in with three and a half somersaults with Tuck, 3.4 for the only German now remaining in the competition.
Oh, precise, steady, unfaltering, and unwavering.
Big dive for Patrick, 3.4.
He's quite tall for a diver, so he needs to get his technique spot on, and he does just that.
Moving a safe, safe distance from the diving board.
Maybe a little bit too far away actually.
Struggled a little bit with his entry into the water.
If he gets a bit nearer and a bit higher he could get nines.
Seven and a half so for that one.
78.20 the total mark goes over the 300 points for Patrick Housding.
Alexei Pigorov started with a very high dive.
This is a high tariff of two.
3.5 on the reverse, three and a half somersaults.
Pigorov almost crashing out of the semi-finals there.
He did a great job though in the end.
Let's have a look at this takeoff.
Yeah, just skips forward.
I don't know whether you see that.
Skipping off at the knees and the hips and hangs on for dear life and just about sneaks.
And that is sneaky.
That must have hurt his back.
Yeah, that'll definitely jar his back.
But as divers, we're used to being beaten up by the gym and the water and occasionally after the competitors.
Just the way he adjusted his body when he was going in there.
You know, he feels like snapping his spine the way he went in like that.
Yeah, you just need to be tough when you're a diver.
Reverse three and a half somersaults for Garcia of Spain.
Oh, better effort there from Javi.
Needed a big one and a good one to get it in.
And that's certainly what he's done with his fourth fourth round.
A reverse three and a half.
It's a big dive.
Squeezing in.
Beautiful elevation.
Pops his feet up and slips into the water.
Without much of a trace.
Seventy-eight points.
Time to work out what the Canadian coach is doing.
Why is he clapping that when he's Spanish?
Oh, I didn't notice.
I'm sorry.
I was hoping that I got my points prediction correct, which I did.
We might even pay you at the end of the week if you're lucky.
Chris Colwell, reverse one and a half somersault, three and a half twist.
I think it's the first time we've seen this dive.
3.4 is the degree of difficulty in the free position.
Again, we haven't seen a free dive.
You can explain that after we've seen it.
It's very much a classic dive for any multiple twisting dive less than one and a half somersaults or one and a half somersaults or or less it is in the free position because you don't hold a position a pike or tuck for longer than half a rotation so it just squares it up nicely in the end 3.4 degree of difficulty you don't see I think you might be the only competitor choosing to use this one and a game of tactics working for Colwell there 3.4 it's a good dive
Yeah.
What do the judges think?
New set of judges, of course.
They've gone with the eights.
81.4.
Hang on a second, matey.
Rosset is gone.
Here he goes.
Oh, what a die for Rosset.
No, he wanted to get that one in.
He made a real
of his second round dive and now he's come out all guns blazing.
This is the comeback king.
He's going to absolutely sail above 85 points, buries his entry there, slipping into the water.
He's hardly throwing up any splash.
Wow.
This is the way to get yourself back in contention.
Am I allowed to hold up a card?
Say I'm not ready.
Ask him to do it again.
No, I don't think you want to do it again.
That was brilliant.
87.50.
It was brilliant.
And Rossi has really recovered so well.
Francois Imbeu-Dulac.
His biggest dive so far.
3.5 degree of difficulty.
Reverse three and a half somersaults with tuck.
He has some work to do to get into the top 18.
25th of the moment.
Roy's done well with it.
Notice there his pre-dive routine.
He tends to stop there, take a big breath, close his eyes, potentially visualize the dive, and then he sets off.
Very composed.
He is a little bit tight to the diving board here, I might add.
He's okay.
He turns into a bit of a frog kick as he comes out.
The breaststrokers would have been pleased with that one.
Anyway, that's a good dive and it's his highest degree of difficulty.
Hanging on to the top of his kneecap.
So look at those frog's legs as he comes out.
Rabbit.
That's very unkind.
We'll start talking about your personage in a moment.
Now onto Ilya Zakharov.
This man has been the model of consistency.
Standby for commentators curse.
No, he is consistent even with a dodgy takeoff.
No smiles from the Russian coaches.
They're here to do business way back from the end of the diving board and I did think that he'd struggle with that but he is superb.
That can be even better.
He needs a better hurdle step on his next dive, because he adds another twist to that dive, which goes up to 3.9 degree of difficulty.
Anyway, we'll tee that out.
That's 81.
I can't believe the succession of scores.
86, 84, 82, 81.
Just don't get measured up for that.
Alexander Departee.
Inward three and a half somersaults with Tuck, the top Canadian, three point four degree of difficulty.
It's a good dive, little short vertical but this is the dive that Alex hit his head on.
This is the dive that six weeks ago he smacks his head into the springboard.
It would have been about this point that he would have connected with the diving board and scalped himself 21 stitches on his forehead and he's here today
six weeks later showing true courage and true class and he's still in the hunt to make it through.
Not enjoying it today but he'll get through.
He'll get through.
You can tell he's not enjoying it.
Look on his face tells you that when he's uh on top of his game.
He's all smiles and waves but today it's uh just get the job done.
Oh, the Ukrainians rocking and rolling alongside the Russians.
They've got some big, big dives.
All of them have.
They are busting it out today and yeah, nowhere to hide and everyone needs to keep up with them.
Well, I wonder if they can hold this consistency throughout the prelims and the semis and into the final.
Of course, the scores do not carry.
So, whatever the divers do today, it's about shuffling the pack and earning a berth into the semifinals.
Russia won.
Ukraine three at the moment in terms of the pecking order with China in second with her charm.
Uh via Castaneda of Columbia.
It's a big dive.
Really big dive.
Standing backwards, it's 3.5 because you don't get the hurdle step to assist you as you do on the reverse three and a half.
This is a standing start, if you will.
Wow, he does very well there.
Squeezes in, runs out of room a little bit.
Well, I'm very impressed.
That's good.
He's got some big degrees of difficulty coming up.
Now, what do the judges have to say about that?
Coach wants to give him a bit of a cuddle already.
68.25 is his total marks.
Well, you might have guessed, the first of the two Brits.
Here's Chris Mears standing on the three-meter springboard, waiting to perform.
Here's a forward two-and-a-half somersaults with two twists, the most consistent of the two Britons today.
21st at the moment.
Oh, it's a decisive dive, and he's nailed it when he needed to.
Yeah, Tom likes it, and I agree with Tom Daley.
It's a good dive for Mears.
Fourth round needed to be good.
Attacks it out into the double twist, down into the pike, ripping that entry.
That's it, back in contention, maybe even back in that all-important top 18.
Super slow motion.
Can't even keep up with it in slow motion, can we?
No, it's great.
Really great.
Well done, Chris.
Good stuff.
Eights across the board.
Eighty one point six zero and it's giving himself a really good chance now with that.
It's two more rounds still to go.
As we look at the former Chinese now Malaysian going for a reverse three and a half somersaults with tuck.
Oh, he's done years and years and years of training.
He does look a little bit, well he doesn't quite look as sharp as he used to in his younger days.
Here we are, reverse three and a half, 30 years old, squeezing into that tuck shake, popping his feet up, just needed to be a little bit higher for that rip entry into the water.
It'll get over 75 points though and it'll certainly keep him in the mix for a semi-final spot, easily actually.
77 for Jack Wong.
Now Jack Law, you know, as you look around and take up the plaudits of the crowd, you have some work to do here.
Laddie, 17 years of age, a star in Harrogate, European junior champion just a few years ago for three and a half somersault.
This needs to be good.
Oh, he's just maybe feeling the pressure.
It needs to be better than that.
Come on, Jack.
You're double world junior champion, double junior European champion.
You've been in these senior competitions.
Now you are the youngest competitor and there's more to come.
more to come from this young man.
He's not going to move up the field with this.
This is going to keep him outside the top eighteen.
That's going to put a lot of pressure on his two dives to come but I'm confident that he can respond.
Do you know what?
I think I look on the face of Jack tells you really all you need to know at this stage.
I think he thinks like we're starting to think that perhaps he's not going to be returning tomorrow.
I hope that's not the case.
No, he will be.
Nineteenth place after a really, really poor start.
He's done a good reparation job, not quite complete though yet.
In with three and a half somersaults with tuck, three point four degree of difficulty.
He's in 19th place after round three.
Oh, here you go.
You're going to up the degree of difficulty, increase the risk, and obviously increase the probability of error.
And that's what we see here from the young diver of Greece, squeezes into the touch shape, just stays in it too long, and lands in a forward roll position.
Yeah, over he goes, and down the marks go.
Hm, what a shame.
What a shame because he was doing so well, but not going to miss to found us his day, I'm afraid, with those marks.
That's going to take him pretty much out of contention for a top 18 place.
There's Tommaso Rinaldi still has a chance.
But again, this has to be one of his games.
A 3.0 as well.
Reverse two and a half, Somersault with Pike.
He's done really well there.
Sneaking the dive in.
Looked as though he was going to go over a vertical on the entry but he just bends at the hips and bends at the knees to get it in.
All good so far.
Great aerial work.
Beautiful pike.
Elegant exit.
Just tips over but tries to sneak it in.
I wonder if the judges will let him get away with that.
They might only give him sevens or he might sneak some eights.
Interesting.
Have you ever done any judging?
Uh me?
Hang them and flog them judge wouldn't you be sticking in there going, I spotted that.
I know your little tricks.
Maybe I think you would.
Chin Kai for China in with three and a half summer slots with Tuck.
The Chinese has probably not been quite in the top form today.
It's starting to get things going.
Yeah, it's good.
And you know, well, he likes it.
Chinese contingent there.
Many of them a big entourage to support this team.
And of course, in this contest in 25 hours time, we'll be looking for six out of six at the moment.
King Kai battling out with the rest of them for those semi-final spots.
And that's certainly going to help his cause.
He'll sail over 80 points without 3.4.
I've seen it better, but it doesn't need to be any better than that to make it through today.
Yeah, number one.
Got one and three.
The Chinese now.
The order has changed.
Zakharov off the top spot for the first time.
And China one and three.
Russia in number two with Zakharov.
Now Troy Dumay, who is in a very good position to be returning from the top A team.
Nothing goes wrong on the final two dives.
Three dives.
He'll be fine.
Inward three and a half somersaults with tuck three point four.
Yeah, it's good from Demay.
He is a little low on the water.
Some of the other divers completing the dive with much more time to spare.
Demay, a little bit low.
Here we go.
Squeeze one, two, three.
You can see way below the board as he finishes, but he's so neat and tidy and he sneaks it in there.
Well, there you go.
Seventy-five points plus.
I think so.
What you mean is you know so, don't you?
The inbuilt totalizer in your in your brain does that.
The inbuilt totalizer.
I love that.
Seventy-eight point two zero.
Not quite sure where that came from.
of Mexico is having a really good competition.
Third place after the last round.
Reverse three and a half
Oh, yes.
It's good.
He just maybe going loose in his lower back as he kicked out of the dive there.
So, he will not be getting nines but the aerial works good.
Look at that.
Way above the five meter.
Squeeze that.
Look, just lower back arch there but he does sneak it in.
Yeah, that'll uh safe passage.
Well, he's done all the hard work early on, so he's got a bit of room for maneuver in terms of not being quite on top of his game now, but that should be fine and should be OK. Robert Paez Rodriguez reverse three and a half somersaults for the Venezuelan.
Oh, well done, Rodriguez.
He's moving around a little bit there as he was coming into the end.
I wasn't quite sure where he was going to land on the end of the diving board, but he ended up all right.
Maybe corner board on the far side, and he plays the waiting game and just plonks that one on his head.
That'll be his biggest scoring dive.
Look right on the corner.
We've seen what happens from there sometimes, but that's a good dive.
Well done, Rodriguez.
let's see what the marks are big smiles from the judges still waiting for them to come up on our screen here they are and yeah that's a biggest score by a long way 63 his previous best 80.5 so bendessi won't wait for me either oh no he won't and neither should he because he just wanted to get that one in he's finishing up the competition he's the guy who has to wait the longest
And he just wants to get his dives done.
Aerial work is good on this.
He's a little bit scruffy as he exits the dive.
Look at this.
Losing his feet a little bit.
But he does get it together on the end.
It's OK.
If he gets over 70 points, he'll stay there or thereabouts.
So some divers with some work to do.
Michele, I think he'll be, where is he?
Yeah, 17th.
Alright, let's find out after we see the Bendetti score.
Yeah, hard day at the office, isn't it?
Really tough work.
Who's there?
Who's anywhere and who's nowhere at this stage after round four?
Chinkai moves into first place.
Chong in third place.
Zakharov still looking very consistent near the top.
Kamashchuk, too, of Ukraine.
That's the top ten.
And Departee is moving into the top ten, where he deserves to be.
Now, who else is there and who's not?
Chris Mears is.
Now, we don't at the moment see Jack Law on that page because Netsov has moved outside the top 18 after such a good start as well.
It's amazing how this second half can undo all the good work.
Francois Imboulou-Dulac has got some work to do, as have everybody on that screen.
And of course, we've lost Stefan Fek after the last round.
He's not performing anymore.
An idea of this rather beautiful aquatic sensor.
It did cost a lot of money, but it's very, very different.
And everybody has given it huge plaudits, but the diving board is exactly the same as anywhere else.
Three meters, and here comes Ethan Warren's reverse three and a half.
Oh, it's a good dive for Warren.
Fifth round.
His four dives so far have been good.
I've seen him diving better in training.
He didn't quite land with his feet together on the end there.
One foot in front of the other.
A little bit peculiar but he squares it up alright in the end.
And yeah, he just needs to continue to get his last dive in on his head and he will make it through.
Steady diving for Warren.
More to come I think from this Australian.
Yeah, just warming up.
And again, a big smile from the Australian.
So he knows the job is virtually done, if not quite done yet.
Damien Sealy of France, 19th after round four.
One of those just flirting with danger and not returning from the top 18.
Back three and a half somersaults with Tuck.
And we're up there in the high tariffs, 3.5 on this one.
Oh, it's a little bit scruffy and this could be good for the home advantage of the British boys, both of which are fighting with this young French man to get into the top eighteen.
It's a big dive.
It's one of his biggest three point five.
Just a little turn as he goes into the water though.
I don't know whether the judges will go to town on him and by go to town on him, I mean take marks off.
If you get sevens and seven point fives, you'll get over seventy
Oh, I don't know which way it's going to go for some of these divers.
As expected, tight.
Judges think sevens.
73.50 after you multiply that with the degree of difficulty.
That's how you get that total.
And just to recall and recap, you don't get those marks with the lines through them included in the score.
Top and bottom scores, multiplied by the degree of difficulty.
Now, He Chong, the big one, a 3.8, forward four and a half.
No, that's how you do it.
He makes it look so easy.
And let me just be clear for you all at home.
That is one of the most difficult dives possible from the three meter springboard.
And look how he almost goes up to seven point five meters.
How is that possible?
Well, it is because her tongue has always been that strong.
We liken him to Sir Chris Hoy with the size of his thighs in relation to the rest of his body and that could get 90 points.
Let's see.
Mm hmm.
Ninety-one point two zero eight.
Still not happy with it though but um never happy.
I know we haven't seen any tens yet in any of the competitions this week.
I'm sure we'll see them when he gets the semis in the final surely now because nets off.
Last dive might have done for his chances
the damage here.
Back two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists.
Oh, that will help.
That will help.
He's one of the well, my front runners.
I expected him to see him well in the business end of the field and instead, he's flapping around outside the semi-final places.
So, the tape holding him together, one and a half twist, two and a half somersaults goes in.
A few people asking about the judges, you're going to see seven marks come up on your screen.
The two highest and two lowest are taken away.
Those are the marks with the lines through them.
Those three marks that count are added together, multiplied by the degree of difficulty to give the total, in this case, of 74.25.
Sorry, we're getting a lot of questions about the tape as well.
A lot of people ask you about why so many of the divers are going to be taped up today, and what the purpose of that is, and what kind of advantage that is.
address that a little later on.
We've seen Daniel O'Rourke go for the inward three and a half somersaults.
3.4 performed in the tuck position this time.
Oh, very nice indeed.
The young Mexican diver coming into.
Wow.
The kind of form the Mexicans have been showing.
I mean, he's way off the pace at the moment, but that's a really good dive.
So let's see, in with three and a half in the tuck position.
Very good dive.
So the taping, as I understand, is to add stimulation to the area.
So if you've got a weakness on the lower back or a certain area, it's to add support to keep the blood flow in the area and not to stimulate it in such a way so the diver is very aware of it.
So to add support.
So much strain going through the body.
that some of the divers need holding together.
The ankles, obviously, knees, they're quite obvious.
You've got to support the particular joints.
But along the back, just adding... Oh, hello.
What happened there?
He's in trouble.
He's in big trouble.
He made it.
I think this might be one of the dive that's played again in the bloopers tape because he swings his arms completely the wrong way.
And I've not seen a diver manage to do that before because his technique went to absolute pot.
He was completely out of balance.
Let's look at this.
jumps here we go oh oh oh arms go forward double arm swing and then manages to steady himself just about gets in the tuck and he makes it we saw Stephen Feck absolutely bomb out this young man has managed to save it oh oh oh oh looks like he had a skipping rope wow i'm super impressed well done that man
Well, that's a big dive and he manages to make it with a very peculiar unorthodox technique.
It really isn't the time to do salt, mustard, vinegar, pepper, is it?
When you're on the end of a diving board.
Now on to Cesar Castro.
Brazil.
Inward two and a half somersaults with Pike.
Yeah, it says are finishing strongly.
Only three point zeros for his last dive and for the next two including this one or this one in the next one obviously.
Three point zero.
Inward two and a half in the pike position.
Straight up and down.
He's certainly make it through to the semifinals.
Easy dives to finish and he's up there.
Over seventy points again.
Yeah, he's uh well, he's a model of consistency.
He hasn't really dropped below 70 any once.
Otherwise, everything has been above 70 in his program so far and that's why he'll be returning for the semifinals.
As we see.
on Malaysia and similarly, they're not with quite the high marks.
He has been very consistent all the way
Yes, certainly will be obviously still one more dive to go for Kenny and that went in with three and a half That's his biggest one three point four.
He's nailed it
Squeezing into that tuck shape.
Wow, the consistency and the quality of diving, as I expected, is through the roof, making it very tough to make it through.
There's a few of the key players who are struggling.
Kenny Yo is not one of them.
Well, he's a key player and he's not struggling.
He's in the mix.
and he gets 76.50 and again he's not been lower than 71.3 in any of his dives today Patrick Housding for Germany 8th in Beijing reverse three and a half 3.5 this is worth oh what a dive
Yep, Patrick, as expected, world class in everything he does.
He competes on the platform as well as the springboard.
So not many divers do that anymore, not in this era.
People tend to specialise, but Patrick, very versatile, exceptionally talented diver and proving so today here on the springboard.
Let's see what the judges think about that.
I think it's going to be, well, let's wait for confirmation.
I can guess, but that gives me the confirmation I was looking for.
89.25.
That's my five's best dive in terms of marks.
Alexey Grigorov forward two and a half, two twists.
Yeah, it's good.
Pugerov is diving consistently.
He did look for a moment there.
He needed a little bit more height and rotation on that dive but he manages to squeeze it in.
Here we are.
One and a half somersaults up.
Double twist.
And down into the water.
It's good.
Sevens.
Seven point five maybe.
I think he's a little bit low on the water for more than that.
and the marks are 74.80 for Prigorov.
Thank you Andy Walker, by the way, for the bit of information I required.
The reason that Javier Garcia was getting great applause and so much commendation from the Canadians.
He is training in Canada these days.
That will be why, even though he represents Spain.
Thank you for that.
In with three and a half somersaults with tuck 3.4 is the degree of difficulty.
Nice.
Let's go, Javi.
That's really good.
Working hard.
And it's paying off.
He's in good shape.
He's had good performances all year.
Squeezing in, tuck shape, bending at the hips, bending at the knees.
In these kind of spins, it's really important that the divers dry their hands.
You'll see the small towels that you see them throwing about the place.
That's for drying their hands and their bodies to keep them warm in between dives, but also to keep the grip on the legs when they're spinning around, because you do not want to slip out.
That's a good dive, 81.
Yeah.
And obviously the training regime he seems to have in Canada it's working to his benefit because he's in a comfortable position right now after that dive.
Now Chris Colwell in with three and a half somersaults with tuck 3.4 smile disappearing just for a moment for the Americans face but he's really been enjoying his campaign so far.
Yep, smiling at the back of the board and concentration as soon as you set foot to walk to the end of the diving board.
Concentration face, game face.
Colwell, probably one of his more difficult, in fact, his more difficult dive, but he's just struggled with this one a little bit because he's so tall.
He does a good job there.
He'll only squeeze sevens, I think.
He'll want more than that as he progresses, but he'll certainly be featuring in the semifinal.
Yeah, just a case of booking your place for the top 18.
None of these marks get carried forward to the semifinals, and indeed the same applies to the semifinal to the final.
So just a case of booking your place to return tomorrow.
Sorry if you're hearing noises off from the commentary box.
Distracting for us, I'm sure for the divers as well.
Mattia Rossi, back two and a half somersaults with Pike.
Yeah, Rossi is such a performer.
I'm sure if you can cast your mind back to earlier in this contest where it was nearly all over for this young Frenchman.
He has come back and for dive after dive.
Yeah, he's a strong diver.
This is only three point zero degree of difficulty.
But he does it very well indeed and he'll certainly be going through to the
Sixty-nine for Rossi.
Eight point zero and two seven point fives.
Gonna look overly chuffed with it but it's good enough and he'll be back for more in the semifinals.
This man at the moment though will not.
Francois of Canada.
Forward two and a half somersaults, two twists, pike position three point four degree of difficulty.
Twenty-first after round five.
Oh, that's one of his better dives, and I should think so too, because he actually ups the ante on his final round dive.
This is the forward two and a half somersaults with two twists.
Let's look at the replay into the end of the diving board.
One and a half somersaults, two twists really quickly, easily done into the water.
You saw before he goes there, closing his eyes, visualizing his dive, leaving his visualization quite late.
Lots of divers use visualization, but I've never seen someone do it right on the diving board just before they go.
Anyway, that's one of his best performances so far.
As I should have said, after round four, he was in 21st place.
He's now in 10th place as Ilya Zakharov prepares for his forward two and a half somersaults with three twists.
Oh, it's a big dive.
It is the world's most difficult dive on the springboard.
3.9 degree of difficulty.
You're only going to see a couple of the guys doing this one.
One, two, three twists.
Oh, I don't know how you get out of that alive, but he does.
little bit shorter vertical but because of the degree of difficulty that could get him eighty points seven six and a half seven but it's a big big degree of difficulty high risk only him her chong and one or two others are going to attempt that dive and he really rushed into there as well though there was no preparation time as soon as he got the the go from the ref he was he was off there and uh kind of surprised me with it with the degree of difficulty that has attached to it three point nine that he wouldn't have actually spent a bit more time over it but
So he dives it his way in Alex Departee.
Forward three and a half somersaults.
Pike 3.1.
Alex up into 10th as he prepares to dive number five.
Yeah, it's good from Departee.
Does he have enough degree of difficulty to challenge again for his third Olympic medal?
Only time will tell.
This is simple.
Lots of the divers still using this.
So forward three and a half in the pike position.
Just tipping over a vertical as he goes in there.
He'll still get eight, eight and a halfs, I think.
So technically proficient.
Really, really good.
Yeah, that was a kid you saw in 1998.
The Commonwealth Games in Malaysia being carried head high by Tony Alley.
Remember that?
Yeah, well, I came third in that competition and he was the winner.
So, yes, I do remember.
Sorry to bring that up, Leon.
That's dinner offer tonight then.
Seventy-seven point five zero for day party.
back two and a half somersaults after round four he was in fourth place this one has only three points zero attached to it oh it needed to be a little bit better than that you can see the taping on the back there there's another diver just jumps into uh that's jack actually preparing himself for his next dive here we are on the replay
He needs to squeeze into the pike a little bit deeper there.
Just letting go a little early, arching through the lower back.
Obviously quite a sensitive area.
Taping on the feet as well.
It's like action men being held together by duct tape.
Anyway, he's still in and still with a fighting chance.
Yeah, I think he'll be okay.
It wasn't a great mark, but he's pretty much done all the hard work up to this stage.
And provided he doesn't do a step and feck, he's okay.
Sebastian Castaneda is upping his degree of difficulty 3.5, reversed 3.5 with tuck 22nd right now.
Oh, what a dive.
Very good from the young Colombian, only 20 years old.
This is his big dive.
This is the one where all the risk is going to be.
And actually, that's his best dive of the contest.
Squeezing into that tuck shape, rotating very quickly, pops it on his head.
That'll probably be his highest scoring dive so far.
And it is.
75.25.
Now, you heard the noise before you see the diver.
The diver wearing the Team GB trunks.
Here's Chris Mears, who's enjoying this.
He'll enjoy it even more if he gets through in the top 18 at the moment.
He is in 16th place, Chris Mears.
Inward three and a half somersaults with tuck for round five.
Oh, it's steady.
It's a little bit short as he goes in.
Everyone's on their feet, though.
The Team GB scarf, the Union flag being waved.
Massive support here for Chris Mears.
Inward three and a half, squeezes in.
Seven seven point fives.
It could have been eights and eight point fives if he'd have just waited a little bit longer.
Dives in Southampton with Lindsay Fraser, same coach as Peter Waterfield.
It's a good dive from Chris Mears.
He'll stay in the all-important Top 18.
Yes.
Yeah, 13th at the moment, but there's quite a few divers still to go.
Could knock him down a peg or two.
On to the Malaysian, as we mentioned, he used to dive for China.
Going towards the end of his career, has switched to Malaysia as part of the Syncro team the other day, in with three and a half.
Oh, it's a big one when he needed it.
Big dive, 3.4, and that's his best dive so far.
Showing his experience, performing under pressure, the weight of expectation.
That'll get close to 80 points, high 70s at least.
It's a good dive.
Stepping up when he needs to.
Wang.
The old memory bank works, doesn't it?
He did that all the time.
He was diving for China, and now he's doing it for Malaysia as well.
Jack Law.
Time is running out for qualification for him.
Just two more rounds.
3.5 degree of difficulty back.
Three and a half somersaults with Tuck.
Jack not quite cast to drift yet.
25th place.
Study concentration on this penultimate dive for Jack Law.
oh he's having such a tough day it's one of his better days but really this young man young boy 17 years old is so much better than this this is frustrating watching i can only imagine what his coach ady is feeling
Oh, it's a big dive.
It's on his head.
It's going to sneak sevens.
It's going to get close to 70 points, maybe just over 70 points, but it's not good enough to move him up the field enough to get in the top 18.
What a tough day for Jack.
Oh, come on.
Well, he's only got one more dive to come on.
And time and dives.
Marks are running out rapidly for him.
of Greece.
Well, he was on the Casper qualification.
Then it rather went wrong in the previous round.
Here he is with his reverse three and a half somersaults with tuck.
Oh, get your surfboards out.
The surf is up.
Yeah, the coach said, no, and that's what happens.
These are difficult dives.
Such a shame.
Here we go.
On the end of the diving board, squeezing into the tuck shape as he spins backwards towards the diving board.
Just let's go way too late.
Here comes the splash.
Moving back towards the diving board.
There we go.
Whoops-a-daisy.
Not going to be his day.
No representation for Greece in the semifinals, it would seem.
Now, the Italian here also has some work to do.
We're in that part of the field now where
They need to pick up big marks.
Reverse two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists for Rinaldi.
Oh, Rinaldi's okay.
Yes, he's can't really afford to be giving away any points and he's a little short as he goes in the water there.
This is one of his bigger dies.
Three point three.
There's a one and a half twist into the two and a half somersaults.
Yeah, needed to be a little bit better than sevens I think and that's what you'll get for that.
short.
Just a little bit.
You say a real Cheltenham then when you said short.
That's Tommaso Rinaldi with um yeah that kind of look that says might not be tomorrow for me.
Here we go.
Big dive.
This is huge.
Three point eight forward four and a half.
Not quite the three point nine we saw previously but three point eight forward four and a half.
Oh dear, dear, dear, dear, dear.
Just goes to show that even the Chinese can go disastrously wrong.
You do not see that very often.
Making a real mess up of his hurdle step just about stays on the end of the diving board.
One foot slipping off.
This is 3.8.
You can't do this off a poor start.
Oh, there we go.
Wow.
Did he complete the dive?
He did complete the dive.
It's fine.
It's only going to get four.
I don't know.
I'd give that a two, two and a half maybe.
Interesting to see what the judges do with that because they would not be expecting that.
One and a half to four.
Come on, judges.
That's ridiculous.
That is a ridiculous spread.
I'm sorry.
What are you watching?
That is a ridiculous spread.
That doesn't make any sense.
The judges were confused.
But anyway, let's see.
I'm confused by the judges.
Troy Dumay, reverse three and a half somersaults with Tuck.
Anything can happen in this competition.
It's getting a little bit bizarre, isn't it?
Oh, Dumay bringing it back on track, nailing his reverse three and a half.
Yeah, it's all about consistency.
And that is what Troy Dumay has been displaying every time he's set foot on the diving board.
So far, these Olympic Games, that's another good dive.
They'll get way over 80 points.
And so it should.
Wow.
Here we go.
What's going to happen in the final round?
Just a few more dives of this round, and then the drama of the final round.
Well, he's done all right.
He's been quite consistent all the way through.
That's his biggest mark of the day.
85.75 for Troy Doumay.
It's actually poetic, I didn't realise that.
I hope he's back tomorrow, I can get a chance to say it again.
Backward, two and a half somersaults with Pike.
Only 3.0 on this one.
Yeah, this is one of his weaker dives.
All divers have to do a dive in a different direction.
So all five groups must be covered.
This is the backwards group.
Backward, two and a half somersaults.
Yael opting for only 3.0.
Lots of the divers opting for this one.
And I've seen it better than that, but I've also seen it a lot worse.
So I don't think that's going to break 70 points, which is where he really needs to be if he wants to stay with the big boys.
Pardon me.
67.50 for Huerta.
I shouldn't know what you were talking about after that.
Robert Paez Rodriguez going for a reverse two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists from Venezuela, 28th after round four.
And that's not going to see him move up from that kind of placing in the standings.
He's only 18 years old, the second youngest.
The only person younger than him is Jack, Jack Law from Team GB, who's having a tough day at the office.
This guy's a bit well all over the place in the nicest possible way, but he's young and he's got plenty of learning.
Plenty of training to go before he gets that consistency.
57.75.
He's got one more dive to come and that will be it and it will be goodbye for him.
Michele Bendetti, give me a bit more time to introduce him this time.
Reverse two and a half somersaults with one and a half twists.
Pike position 3.3 degree of difficulty.
It's a crucial dive for Michele.
and he's made it count.
Always difficult right at the end of the field.
You have to wait and wait and wait and wait and watch all the other divers lodge their scores and then you need to come out and respond and Mickey has done just that.
He's landed on his head.
He'll get seven and a halfs and eights and so he should.
It's a good dive.
I think those are like electrode pads on his lower back, suffering a little bit with lower back pain.
So plug him into the electricity and help him out, I think.
Well, he's a bit of a battery charge, but that might be OK. 18th place, so he's in the very last qualification place after that dive.
End of round five.
And here is how it looks.
Hechong.
Let's just see where the other Chinese is now after that last dive.
Russia, USA, Germany, Mexico, Ukraine, USA again, Malaysia, Canada, Spain.
Now, where is the second Chinese?
There.
There you go, 11th.
And Chris Mears is in.
As you can see on your screen, no place at the moment for Jack Law.
Michele Bendetti is getting the last of the positions at the moment, but that's quite tight.
Because Netshoff won't be back the way things stand.
Oh, Castaneda, Rinaldi, or indeed Jack Law of Great Britain and Stefan Fek, in case you're wondering.
Well, you didn't see him.
He pulled out of the competition after round two.
That's after round three I think it was.
Lots of the crowd still here and Jack Law has got a lot to do on his last dive.
I think he might have left himself too much to do.
He needs the dive of his life to entertain this home crowd.
Chris Mears still in the mix and this is the first diver.
First dive, final round of the men's three meter springboard preliminary.
It's Ethan Warren of Australia for two and a half somersaults, two twists, pike, 3.4 degree of difficulty.
Yeah, he's been steady this evening.
Uh the challenges, these divers all now need to, well, go back to the Olympic Village, have a bite to eat, go to bed, try and get to sleep because they've got to do it all again the next morning.
Well, eighteen of them have and I'm pretty sure that this young man, Ethan Warren of Australia will be one of those.
We'll see as this round progresses when the big Q comes alongside their name, who's qualified.
We'll tell you that as it appears on our screen.
Ethan Warren is pretty much in there without too much difficulty.
441.50 should get it done for him.
Damien Sealy of France though, in 20th place, needs to improve with a reverse two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists.
Well, they looked like he was driving a bus a little bit then.
So, arms are going everywhere, swinging around a little bit in his pike shape.
It wasn't the elegant twisting into the pike that we're used to seeing.
Here we go.
Look, one and a half twist.
Just shoulders, shoulders, shoulders.
In he goes and that may help Jack Law because he is level pegging with him currently.
Little weak dive to finish there.
Weaker dive to finish there from this Frenchman.
Wow, drama.
Obviously in his case, no more room on top.
61.05.
It could be a wave goodbye because he looks like he's not going to be returning for the top eighteen.
What her thought about is uh compatriot really flunking that fifth round dive.
He doesn't got to concern himself but that's an individual competition and he's doing pretty fine.
Thank you.
in first place after round five.
This is forward two and a half somersaults with three twists in the pike position.
Oh, it's, yeah, it's good.
I'm so impressed with this dive.
He does always just split his legs just before he goes in.
Wu Minxiao there, six times Olympic medalist, just a little bit confused as to why her teammate did that.
Here's the triple twist, just about gets it done and then splits his legs.
Oh, he's a bit here and there on the finish.
It might get over 80 points.
I think it would need to be better than that as he progresses.
That's a save.
It's a little bit of a save.
So he kind of gets in and then rolls in the water there to give the impression of being out by but he askew as he goes in.
Yeah, he doesn't like it.
Look at that.
He doesn't like that, does he?
Tempo, tempo.
Eighty-three point eight five for He Chong.
It's always perfection with the Chinese.
Anything less is not acceptable.
And he's gone for it.
He has been a bit here and there during this preliminary and that's his biggest dive.
3.8 and he's done a very good job on it.
Now will it be enough?
He's got that blue tape holding him together.
now has he held it together enough to get through that's going to be a big big score to finish let's see how that affects his total marks now we get to see the mark just before it comes up on your screen that's why i went oop sorry kind of preempted the 91.20 you see on the screen i think that could be enough you know just to sneak him in there 440 that is good
So that may will be enough.
Daniel Arroyo of Mexico, however, needs something similar.
He's got a forward four and a half somersaults.
3.8 tuck.
24th after round five.
This has to be pretty much spot on.
Oh, it is.
It's a good dive.
You're just letting the dive go over as he goes into the water.
But that's not a surprise because it's so difficult to do.
Good hurdle step.
Landing right on the end.
Up, up and away.
Way above the five meter.
Beautiful tuck shape.
And that's one of his best dives.
Just letting the dive go over a vertical, which means he'll get less than sevens probably.
Judges say spread their five up to seven.
One judge didn't like it.
The rest of the judges were were consistent.
Contreras Bracho of Venezuela 27th and again unlikely to return unless this is spectacular 3.3 reverse two and a half somersaults one and a half twist he's gone again now what happens now okay so that is a technical restart you can see the crowd getting behind the athlete so what will happen the diver will perform the dive as stated
He will be marked out of 10 by each of the judges and then there will be a two-point deduction from each of the judges before it's multiplied by the degree of difficulty.
So you will not see that on screen, you will just see it in the total score.
The reason he stopped is because he was all over the shop again on his hurdle step.
We have seen some drama, haven't we?
Yeah, from this guy in particular.
In the last dive, he made it without an arm swing.
He's got an awful hurdle step again.
Oh, that is a real calamity.
An absolute shambles, actually.
Let's call it what it is.
He's going to get two points deduction from the raw scores, which are going to be really, really low.
What an absolute shame.
We've seen it all today.
We've seen Stephen Feck have to pull out of the competition because he slipped off the diving board and failed his dive.
We've seen this guy stop, get the restart, and then, wow.
Has he got the tension on the board wrong?
There seems to be way too much movement on that.
No, no, no.
He's just an awful takeoff.
No, he's yeah.
Look at that.
A total of four point nine five.
I've not seen a dive score that low.
He's distraught ever.
That's actually of course.
Oh, you got a feel for him.
Absolutely distraught.
Hmm.
That's the ups and downs literally of diving.
And I think you'll be consolable for quite some time.
competition moves on.
However, we're Cesar Castro, our Brazil reverse two and a half Salasorts with Pike.
Oh, it's a very good dive to finish from Cesar needed to be.
He's only just in the semi-final spot if you like.
So, he's fifteenth after the five rounds.
This is three point zero.
He is doing his dives very well indeed and he needs to low degree of difficulty in
Very elegant, quite a tall diver, very experienced, 29 years old, one of the oldest competitors, using his experience and making it through safely.
441, there's a lot around that score.
There are, yeah, we've got 441s, 440s, 500 as well, which is her charm.
Now to the Malaysian, Kenny Yo is approaching the 400 mark himself.
Here's the back two and a half somersaults with Pike for him.
No worries for Kenny.
He's rocking and rolling.
He's straight through to the semifinals.
eight after the fifth round and uh yeah, good performance from this young man today.
I say young man, young man of 29 years old, one of the oldest competitors that he was on the money today.
Consistent.
That's what you need to be.
He has been a model of consistency.
71, 81, 72, 79, 76, and another 72 to round it off.
We'll be welcoming Ken back to the semifinals, as I think we will be, provided nothing goes untoward here.
Patrick Housling's reversed two and a half somersaults, two and a half twists.
Wow, what a dive.
Should have made a bit more of a fuss of this one.
3.7 degree of difficulty.
He's actually adding a twist to what a lot of the other divers here.
Two and a half twists.
Two and a half somersaults.
3.7 is a huge dive.
And that'll easily get over 80 points because of the degree of difficulty.
And that's Housding through.
Stephen Feck out.
Yeah, waiting for the queues to come beside the names.
They haven't actually happened as yet, but they will be because we've got so many competitors, 29 of them, but I think you can safely assume that Patrick Housding will return.
I'll go out on a limb.
I don't think you will have to go out on a limb for that one.
Alexei Prigorov, 13th place.
A bit of a margin for everyone on this one.
Oh, it looked like he was going to do a bit of a marginal error, but he managed to hang on, played the waiting game.
He could sense that his rotation was a little bit slow.
Here we go up.
Here's the one and a half twist.
And then he squeezes and thinks, oh, hang on a minute.
I'm spinning slow.
I better bury my face in my shins and hang on for the ride, which is what he does.
Just about gets in there.
Well, he diverts anything.
Oh, yeah.
He made it through.
They could look.
Yeah, he just about did it.
That's great.
69.30.
What you go through on the poolside watching your teammates or your sons or daughters.
Yeah, because you can't influence what's going on up there.
It's Garcia's last dive.
He reversed one and a half, three and a half twists.
Oh, a nice dive to finish from Javi.
Reverse one and a half somersaults, three and a half twists.
This is a classic dive.
This is what we used to see 10 years ago longer before the multiple somersault, multiple twists came in.
But this is a beautiful dive.
It is 3.4 now degree of difficulty.
And Javi making it count there.
Nice dive to finish.
Wouldn't have been that longer.
20 years ago, all the divers would have used this dive.
Last two dives, both the same mark.
81.60.
No product placement here, thank you.
460.35 from him.
Now Chris Colwell.
8th in Rome, 9th here in February when he took part in this competition.
One Grand Prix win this year in Fort Lauderdale on his way to the semis if the reverse three and a half works to his advantage, 3.5 degree of difficulty.
Oh yeah, what a dive from Colwell to finish.
It's a big one.
Reverse three and a half.
Lots can go wrong, and we've seen that already from many of the other competitors, but Colwell making no mistakes there on his final dive.
Beautiful dive.
Will it get 80 points?
I don't think it'll be too far away.
Yes, it does.
80.50.
8 and 7.5.
So, mind you, if you are late coming to this, all the marks with lines through them do not count.
Bottom marks, top marks disappear.
It's the ones in the middle.
Rosset's final forward two and a half somersault, two twists.
Well, we'll say the comeback king just missing his hands as he goes in there throwing up too much splash but he fought his way back into the top eighteen after a complete calamity on his second round dive.
I think it was it's unusual to get the charge just missing his hands as he went in throwing up a bit of splash on his forward two and a half there two
has got lots to offer and I'm glad to see him going through to the semi-final because if he's on he's going to be up there look at that just saying to his coach he clapped his hands he went in that's why there was lots of splash 4.45 not the most animated of drivers doesn't need to be you can save all that kind of stuff for tomorrow once he knows he's through and he pretty much is now Francois Imboul Dulac
of Canada.
Nineteenth after dive number five.
Made up a couple of places so knows he's almost there but this is huge.
3.9 degree of difficulty.
Forward two and a half salasaults.
Three twists.
Hold on.
This could be a bumpy ride.
Whoa, I do not believe it.
That is absolutely monumental.
What a dive.
Wow, I did not see that coming.
Look at the smile and so it should be.
This is 3.9.
Wow, one and a half somersaults.
Here come the triple twist.
He's saved his best till last, and that's going to get a massive score.
Wow, I was not expecting that.
I was expecting to how I could hear the helicopters overhead, and I was thinking of a helicopter joke to boot, but no need for a helicopter joke.
What a dive.
And you just heard Leon Taylor's voice break on air.
Fantastic.
93.60.
Yeah.
Now, Zakharov.
Oh, the danger man.
He split the Chinese in Shanghai last year.
Gold to China, silver to this man and then bronze to China.
Will he feature again and certainly doing a formidable job here this evening.
We're going to do the same again tomorrow twice but if that's anything to go by, he's on form.
I'm tempted to say that so far, can we just fast forward to round six, please?
Because we're getting some sensational dives in this round, are we?
Zakharov, 91.20.
Imboudounak, 93.60.
Alex Departee, forward two and a half somersaults to Twist, 3.4 to finish.
Yes, Alex's best dive just moving over vertical as he goes into the water.
Yeah, he's certainly not happy Alex today, but it's the prelims.
You know, he's a perfectionist.
That's why he's double Olympic silver medalist in this event.
He knows he needs to dive better.
That'll get him enough to get through.
and if he ups his game tomorrow morning and ups it again for the final, he could feature but has he got enough degree of difficulty?
We will wait and see.
Didn't have the grace of starts but he's finishing with a great deal of pluck and vigor, encourages, he always does and he'll be back for more in the semis as will Ilya Kavasha of Ukraine.
Forward two and a half
Yeah, well, he was all over that.
And it was a really, really good dive.
Yeah, attacking the end of the diving board.
Really, really strong.
Out.
Double twist.
Completing the dive.
Super smooth entry into the water with a rip.
80 points plus.
And a secure place in the semi-final early tomorrow morning.
It's pretty harsh, isn't it?
Tomorrow morning.
Let's confirm who's there.
Zakharov, Hechong, Housding, Kavasha, Colwell, Garcia, Departee, all with Q's beside their names.
There will be many more shortly, but they are all definitely through.
Mathematically, they cannot be overtaken, so all those seven have made it through.
now castaneda 22nd in with three and a half somersaults with tuck 3.4 degree of difficulty might just agree himself a little bit too much to do
Yeah, just rolling over the dive there.
This is what happens.
These competitions are so long, people start to lose it a little bit.
Maybe it's concentration, maybe it's fatigue.
Some divers raise in their game, others faltering.
This young man, only 20 years old, he'll be back again.
And you can hear the crowd behind me as I'm speaking because who's up next?
Can you guess?
Castaneda finishes in 300.
Just checking those marks again.
Let's take it off the screen before I get a chance to give it to you.
400, sorry, 413.60.
Now, Chris Mears, this is the big one, the very big one.
This will be the difference between you making that semifinal and not.
They can hardly watch.
Forward, four and a half somersaults with tuck.
Big degree of difficulty.
3.8 for Chris Mears.
Oh yes, I think it's going to be good enough.
The crowd are behind him.
Tom and Stacey, Sarah Barrow, teammates on their feet.
That's a good dive.
It's his biggest degree of difficulty, 3.8.
We've seen lots of the other divers nail it.
We've seen some of the divers falter.
Chris does tip over a vertical, throwing the splash up a little bit away from you.
He does a good job.
Hopefully that is enough.
it's not going to get more than sevens unfortunately but oh I'm hoping that he doesn't get sevens six point fives for Chris Mears doesn't get sevens got marked down there maybe just a tad maybe we're just being a bit um jingoistic good word now there's a man who's just about there but not quite there if you know what I mean
Oh, he's finishing strongly.
Was he in 17th?
Yes, 17th after the fifth round.
Crunk showing his experience.
It's a big dive.
3.4.
Oh, wow.
This is going to be tight for those remaining spots.
And this guy is certainly in the hunt for one of those.
Well, let's see his marks.
And I'll tell you who else has definitely made the semifinals after this.
73.10 in Budulac and Rosset the latest names with a Q beside their names.
That means the top 10 are confirmed.
Eight places still to go for definite.
Jack Law, slightly forlorn look on his face because it's only 3.4.
Really has to be the top of his game here.
Forward two and a half somersaults, two twists.
Oh dear, dear, dear.
Jack.
Oh no.
Oh Jack.
He's just had, well, what happened there?
He landed on the end of the diving board, completely almost slipped off, mistimed.
There we go, just buckles, knees buckle, went for the big one.
There's no rotation, nothing he can do.
He just wants to swim away, wants to disappear.
I really, really feel for him.
He's only 17.
He has got so much potential.
That happens in training.
You get a knee buckle completely.
and I I really feel for him.
There's nothing he could do.
He's had a really bad day.
He's had an awful day of diving.
He failed his failed his last dive.
My goodness.
Can't wait to go and uh they're chasing after him but I think he'll be long gone because he just wants to get out of here and you have to understand why that would be.
The crowd have gone absolutely
Oh, it's a wonderful dive for the Greek to finish on.
One of his easier dives again, the 3.0, and he's executed it just with precision.
This is what we're looking for.
Rip entries into the water.
His aerial work is good.
You can't see any light or daylight in between the chest and the thighs, and he rips the entry.
He's going to get eights.
It's good.
but not good for uh Jack.
Wow.
I'm still reeling after watching that.
Castro and Warren are the latest ones to have queues beside their name.
So, they're through as well.
So, we now know twelve of the eighteen for definite.
So, a few more competitors to go yet though before we can confirm the eighteen but uh up to Warren.
They are all definitely back.
A few people waiting to see what happens in the remaining
Tommaso Rinaldi of Italy in with three and a half somersaults with Tuck, 23rd place after dive number five.
Here's his final attempt.
Oh, I think that's he's left himself a bit much to do.
That needed to be more.
More points than it's going to get.
Just running out of room in with three and a half is his biggest dive.
You can just see here finishing low on the water, not quite straightening out enough.
What will he get?
I don't know.
Five and a half, six and a half, seven maybe.
It's yeah.
I've got to say with this selection of judges, anything's possible.
Yeah, let's see what they think.
Yeah, five point five up to seven point five.
Look at that two point differential there, but only the ones with that.
Over them.
Count.
Because next up, by the way, has got another one of the births for the semifinals.
Shinkai 11th, unbelievably after round five after an almost failed dive.
Oh, that one wasn't his best either.
But it's good enough.
11th, he'll make it through to the top 18.
Some of his teammates, they're a bit confused as to what's going on, as we were in the commentary box.
Taping on the toes, the explanation for that is that toes get worn out.
The diving board has actually got a lot of grip on it.
It's a bit like sandpaper, not quite as harsh as sandpaper.
But when you're doing dive after dive after dive after dive, it does rub away at your toes.
So a lot of the divers using tape on their toes just to replace the skin, I guess.
74.25.
Not a happy bunny at all but he's gonna be back for more and uh an improvement definitely required from Chin Kai for a medal and the final takes place on Tuesday night.
Troy Doumay, forward two and a half somersaults, two twists, pike position, 3.4, he's done pretty much all the hard work so that's just to put the tin lid on his qualification.
Wow he certainly does it in fine style.
puts the tin lid on his qualification.
I like that saying.
I put that into my repertoire.
Here we go for Dume.
Very consistent.
He'll be right up there in the top three with that.
Fantastic diving from the already crowned Olympic medalist earlier in the week and he certainly deserves his spot through in the semi-finals tomorrow morning.
Yeah, there you go, the chinkai.
Troy Dumay is also qualified, so we know 15 of them now.
Only three more to be.
Oh, this is agony for Chris Mears.
Agony, because he knows he's not definitely guaranteed a place yet in the semifinals.
Yeah, Castillo Huerta.
Reverse two and a half, one and a half twist, pike three point three to finish.
Yep, he's in.
No worries for Yal.
I've seen him dive better two years ago.
I thought he was going to be the next big thing.
Hasn't quite lived up to his potential as yet.
So let's wait and see what he's got in store for us tomorrow morning at the semifinals and then if that all goes well in the final later on tomorrow night, local time, easily making it through.
Steady set of dives.
Yeah, very impressive set of dives indeed.
Good effort by the Mexican and he is through.
I can tell you at the moment Chris Mears is in 18th place.
He's got the last one.
Ryan Rodriguez doesn't do something spectacular.
He should remain in 18th place.
Forward two and a half somersaults, two twists, pike position for him.
Oh he finishes on a good one.
The young 18 year old from Venezuela.
I think he's had a really good time today.
I've been watching him in between dives, smiling away, just taking in going, wow, I am in the Olympic Games.
I'm doing what I love to do.
I'm diving.
You know, I'm not going to make it through maybe, but I'm going to give it my all.
And that's exactly what Rodriguez has done today.
71.40.
And I think Chris Mears is going to be just about OK. Well,
Not quite, because if this is around 70 for Bendetti, then Mears is gone.
Forward two and a half somersaults, two twists, Pike 3.4, and he nearly missed his entry as well.
No, his entry is spot on, but his arm swing was all over the shop.
He nearly missed his takeoff, but his entry was good.
Wow, he's holding his head.
He knows how close this is going to be as well.
Just about squares it up on the end of the diving board, completes the dive.
It's a forward two and a half, two twists.
Wow, I don't know which way this is going to go.
It's going to be tough close.
It's either Benedetti in or out, Mia's in or out.
Which way is it going to go?
And the news is Benedetti has missed out in 20th place.
The Italian got that all wrong in terms of the preparation.
And that has opened the door for the home favorite Chris Mears just, and I mean just, to sneak into 18th place.
No place for Jack Law.
But Chris Mears has made it.
And that's the agonized face on Michele Benedetti, who knows he is not.
returning the crowd have seen the scoreboard as indeed you will do in just a moment big hug between coach and diver you won't see it yet the crowd have seen it on the scoreboard chris it's going to be better tomorrow mate but he's there
What a competition that was.
Just getting our breath back.
That was extraordinary.
We've seen everything.
Apart from somebody, God forbid, hitting their head on the dyme anymore.
We've seen everything in that competition.
It just shows the heartbreak.
This is how much it means to these athletes.
Mickey there didn't dive as well as he wanted to today and just ended up on the wrong side of that top 18.
Gutting for him.
Fantastic news for the other divers who have made it through.
Right then.
These are the ones who will return top 18.
Pretty much all the names you might expect.
Although there's only one Chinese at the top there because of
A little bit of an aberration by the other but he will return on page two.
Alexander Departee getting through in ninth place for Canada.
Two Americans safely through.
Chiang Kai too.
He will do well.
Great last dive.
Rosse, Castro, Warren, Kuznetsov, Prigorov and Chris Mears qualifies by less than three points in the end and the Malaysian misses out as does Bendetti but eighteenth place Chris Mears for Great Britain and all these
They'll be thinking about what they're going to do with the rest of their week.
Jack Law included after that last dive that went so wrong.
Stefan Fek bowing out after round three.
What an extraordinary competition.
We can't expect that kind, I would not say calamities, but that kind of excitement and range of emotions surely in the semi-final.
Oh, well, I don't know.
Let's see.
18 divers have made it through.
I'm very surprised not to see Jack Law through and I'm sure he feels absolutely devastated.
Mia's did a great job.
So did many of the other divers.
There were some fantastic dives but lots of things happen.
This is what it's about.
You've got to make it through the preliminary rounds.
you make it through but then of course everything goes to zero so it doesn't matter whether you're Heechong or Chris Mears everyone starts at zero in the semi-finals they've got to get to bed tonight they've got to get some sleep if they can and get up early tomorrow morning to come in and train because the competition starts 10am tomorrow morning local time
You better be with us.
You had better be with us.
Make a date, record it, do whatever you want, but don't be anywhere else.
The semifinals are going to be great.
And the finals in the evening too.
Make sure you rejoin Leon Taylor and myself, Bob Ballard.
Thank you for joining us for an extraordinary night of diving.
I'm sure you'd agree.
Good night.